<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jerub-baal, or, The pleader impleaded being an answer to Mr. Croftons (lately published) plea for communion with the Church under her present corruptions, &amp;c., entituled Reformation not separation by way of humble remonstrance thereunto : shewing, that non-communion with the Church of England in her liturgy and common-prayer, in those that (yet) joyn with her in the substantial ordinances and instituted worship of Christ, is no schism, and that such are unjustly called separatists : in a letter / written by T.P. for the private satisfaction of a friend, and by him published for common benefit.</title>
            <author>T. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12588210</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12588210</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53999)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 674:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jerub-baal, or, The pleader impleaded being an answer to Mr. Croftons (lately published) plea for communion with the Church under her present corruptions, &amp;c., entituled Reformation not separation by way of humble remonstrance thereunto : shewing, that non-communion with the Church of England in her liturgy and common-prayer, in those that (yet) joyn with her in the substantial ordinances and instituted worship of Christ, is no schism, and that such are unjustly called separatists : in a letter / written by T.P. for the private satisfaction of a friend, and by him published for common benefit.</title>
                  <author>T. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672. --  Reformation not separation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63806:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63806:1"/>
            <p>Jerub-baal, OR THE Pleader impleaded.</p>
            <p>BEING An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> (lately publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed) Plea <hi>for Communion with the Church under her preſent Corruptions,</hi> &amp;c. Entituled <hi>Reformation not Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By way of humble <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> thereunto.</p>
            <p>SHEWING, That <hi>Non-Communion with the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>in her Liturgy and Common-Prayer, in thoſe that (yet) joyn with her in the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Ordinances and inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt,</hi> is no <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and that Such are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly called <hi>Separatiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Letter written by <hi>T. P.</hi> for the private ſatisfaction of a Friend, and by him publiſhed for Common benefit.</p>
            <q>In cujus perniciem aliquando convenimus? hoc ſumus congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gati quod et diſperſi, hoc univerſi quod et ſinguli, nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem laedentes, neminem contriſtantes. <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertul. Apolog. adverſus Gent.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed in the Yeare 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:63806:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63806:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Letter</hi> Written by <hi>T. P.</hi> for the ſatisfaction of a Friend, in caſe of <hi>Non-Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Chiſm</hi> being a <hi>diſſolution</hi> and <hi>breach</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> 'twill not be amiſſe, if for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the nature of the <hi>Schiſm</hi> in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, we make ſome enquiry into that <hi>Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> whereof it is a breach: Now, from the <hi>diſtinct notions</hi> and <hi>acceptions</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> the nature of <hi>Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> will beſt appear.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt, (even that which is <hi>Militant</hi> (for the <hi>Triumphant</hi> comes not here to be conſidered) is uſually diſtinguiſhed into
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Catholick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Particular.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Catholick</hi> Church again, into
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Viſible.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Inviſible.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Catholick Viſible</hi> Church is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality</hi> of Perſons <hi>called by the Word</hi> into <hi>External</hi> Fellowſhip with Chriſt, and Communion amongſt themſelves, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the true Religion,</hi> the Faith, Doctrine, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Chriſt throughout the world; called <hi>Viſible</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Outward Adminiſtration</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63806:3"/>2. The <hi>Catholick-Inviſible</hi> Church is the <hi>Collective Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of the truly <hi>Faithfull,</hi> the compleat <hi>Quorum</hi> of the <hi>Elect,</hi> Gods <hi>Choſen</hi> ones, <hi>called</hi> out of the whole World of Mankind, into an intimate <hi>Vnion</hi> with Chriſt, and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> one with another, not only <hi>externally</hi> by the <hi>Word,</hi> but <hi>effectually</hi> and <hi>internally</hi> by Gods holy <hi>Spirit;</hi> called <hi>Inviſible,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quá</hi> Men, but <hi>quá</hi> Elect, the <hi>Man</hi> is ſeen, but not the <hi>Chriſtian: The Lord</hi> (only) <hi>knoweth them that are his,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. The <hi>Church-Catholick</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both thoſe conſiderations, called the <hi>Myſtical Body</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. By <hi>League</hi> &amp; Outward <hi>Profeſſion</hi> under the former; 2. By true <hi>Faith</hi> and real <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> under the latter: <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>Common Head</hi> both to the one, and to the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Particular</hi> Church is a <hi>Society</hi> or <hi>Societies</hi> of Perſons called to the <hi>participation</hi> of, and ſubjected to the Ordinances and inſtituted worſhip of Chriſt, under certain external Rules accommodated for <hi>Local Joynt-Communion</hi> therein, in a <hi>particular place:</hi> Such are the <hi>Engliſh, French, Dutch</hi> Churches, and ſuch like, including <hi>Parochial Diſtributions</hi> and <hi>Congregations</hi> as the Church <hi>Catholick</hi> includes them, <hi>viz.</hi> as a <hi>totum Integrale,</hi> or <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſale,</hi> ſo as that <hi>nec totum recte de una praedicetur, nec una totum ſibi vindicare poſſit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Junius, lib. de Eccleſia;</hi> though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> make a kind of <hi>Monopoly</hi> of their <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, obtruding it for a <hi>Catholick,</hi> yea, the <hi>only Catholick</hi> Church in the World; and thus by a curſed Sacriledge <hi>impropriate</hi> (as I may ſay) the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Diſtinct Notion</hi> of the Church, ariſeth from the diverſified Nature of her <hi>Members</hi> (the <hi>Conſtitutive Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> thereof) who may be conſidered, either 1. as <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of the Faith of Chriſt, in obedience to an <hi>Externall</hi> Call by the <hi>Word;</hi> thoſe conſtitute the Church <hi>Catholick-Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible:</hi> or 2. as <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi> of Chriſt by <hi>Faith (true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers)</hi> in Obedience to an <hi>Internall</hi> Call by the <hi>Spirit;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63806:3"/>thoſe conſtitute the Church <hi>Catholick-Inviſible;</hi> or 3. as <hi>Partakers</hi> of the ſame Ordinances and inſtituted worſhip of Chriſt, in a particular place, in Obedience to a <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential</hi> Call, and in anſwer to an <hi>Opportunity</hi> ſerving there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; thoſe conſtitute a <hi>Particular</hi> Church, ſo that the ſame Perſons may be <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> under that <hi>threefold</hi> conſideration at once.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> then muſt be <hi>threefold,</hi> or conſiderable under a <hi>threefold Notion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Firſt is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the Members of the Church <hi>Catholick-Inviſible,</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> amongſt <hi>themſelves,</hi> wherein they are, through the <hi>Inhabitation</hi> and <hi>Indwelling</hi> of the ſame <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> in all, and by vertue of a <hi>true Faith,</hi> joyntly <hi>incorporated</hi> into Chriſt, and <hi>concorporated</hi> one with another; as <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Members</hi> of the ſame <hi>Select Fraternity,</hi> the Son of God having aſſumed their <hi>Perſons</hi> into a <hi>Myſtical,</hi> as well as their <hi>Nature</hi> into a <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Sir,</hi> This <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> admits of no <hi>breach,</hi> Chriſt and his <hi>Elect</hi> Members (the true <hi>Branches</hi> of that true <hi>Vine</hi>) are <hi>inſeperably</hi> conjoined; their <hi>Perſons</hi> (as well as their <hi>Nature</hi>) are eternally matched and married to Chriſt; the <hi>Myſtical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the one, is <hi>indiſſoluble,</hi> as well as the <hi>Perſonall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the other with him. There is no fear of a <hi>divorce</hi> here; neither can the <hi>Body</hi> be ſevered from the <hi>Head,</hi> nor any one <hi>Member</hi> from the <hi>Body:</hi> the Members may quarrel (an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> with an <hi>Iſraelite</hi>) thus we read that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did conteſt and contend ſo fiercely, that their <hi>Paroxyſme</hi> of ſtrife ended in <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> Act. 15.39. Yea, they may joyn to their breach of <hi>Society,</hi> a breach of <hi>Charity</hi> in ſome degree; but neither is the one nor the other a diſſolution of that <hi>Internal</hi> Union whereby the truly <hi>Faithfull</hi> are coupled together, one with another, and all of them joyntly with their <hi>Common Head,</hi> Chriſt. The <hi>Vinculum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nionis,</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion-Knot</hi> (viz: true <hi>Faith,</hi> or the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of grace
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63806:4"/>in the Faithfull) being altogether <hi>inviolable.</hi> The <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> is the <hi>Fountain-Radical</hi> of Faith, (as of all other Graces) and therefore of this <hi>Communion.</hi> One <hi>Spirit</hi> quickening &amp; influencing both Head and Members in the <hi>Myſtical,</hi> as one <hi>Soul</hi> conveys life and ſenſe to all the Members of the <hi>Natural</hi> Body, (and hence 'tis I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that Chriſt and Beleevers are ſaid to be, not <hi>One Body</hi> onely, but <hi>One Spirit</hi> (viz: <hi>in Eſſe Myſtico</hi>) 1 Cor. 6.17.) Now this ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> may ſuſpend his influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, viz: <hi>Comfortable</hi> and <hi>Augmentative,</hi> not <hi>Vital</hi> (as in the dark and ſolitary dayes of <hi>ſoule-deſertion</hi>) and <hi>Faith</hi> may in ſuch a caſe be much weakened and impaired, (viz: in its <hi>Graduals</hi>) but <hi>True Faith</hi> being the <hi>Seed of God</hi> (1 John 3.9.) is, <hi>in Eſſe vitali,</hi> as to its <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (intrinſecally) permanent,</hi> an <hi>irreradicable</hi> principle, <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance</hi> and <hi>indeficiency</hi> being its <hi>Genuine property,</hi> as well as Chriſts <hi>purchaſe,</hi> Luke 22.32. there is a kind of <hi>Immortality</hi> in it; So that, as there is a <hi>weakneſſe</hi> in the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> Faith, ſo there is <hi>truth</hi> in the <hi>weakeſt;</hi> now this <hi>Vnion</hi> depends not upon the <hi>ſtrength,</hi> but upon the <hi>truth</hi> of Faith; and not upon the <hi>Gradual Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but upon the <hi>Radical Inhabitation</hi> of the Spirit: Such a <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> then, is unfitly termed a <hi>ſeperation,</hi> (<hi>David</hi> loſt <hi>Comfort,</hi> but not the <hi>Comforter,</hi> Pſal. 51.11, 12.) or if we grant (with ſome) that it is (a breach <hi>in tantum,</hi> though not <hi>in totum</hi>) a breach <hi>in,</hi> yet 'tis no interruption or breach <hi>of, Vnion,</hi> but rather a <hi>temporary intermiſſion</hi> of (Comfortable) <hi>Communion.</hi> What though the <hi>Trees of Righteouſneſſe</hi> have their <hi>Autumn</hi>-ſeaſon, their <hi>fall of the leaf</hi> (the trees of the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> as well as thoſe of the <hi>Forreſt</hi>)? There is ſtill an <hi>Indeficient</hi> principle of life in them, by vertue of their inciſion and ingraſture into their Common <hi>Root,</hi> Chriſt, the <hi>Tree of Life.</hi> This is both defenſive and offenſive Armour againſt our <hi>Arminian</hi> Adverſaries, who daringly aſſert a <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Seperation</hi> here, <hi>de poſſibilis;</hi> that is, that 'tis poſſible for the truly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63806:4"/>Faithfull, <hi>totally</hi> and <hi>finally</hi> to apoſtatize from Chriſt, and thus, of true <hi>Converts,</hi> to become very <hi>Caſt-awayes;</hi> ſad doctrine Might we receive what they obtrude for <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy,</hi> verily we might betake our ſelves to our pen, and write our <hi>faith vain,</hi> all our prayers loſt, and <hi>our ſelves of all men moſt miſerable. If the foundation be deſtroyed, what can the Righteous do?</hi> But now here is the Beleevers <hi>Fort-Royal,</hi> namely his <hi>Inviolable Conjunction</hi> with his <hi>Living Head,</hi> Chriſt; this is an impregnable bottom of <hi>Saint-ſtability,</hi> groud of <hi>Chriſtian-perſeverance,</hi> and guard againſt their <hi>total-final Apoſtacy: Quatenus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, munimur,</hi> this <hi>Vnity</hi> is our <hi>Safety.</hi> By vertue of this (to ſpeak a big word) the State of <hi>grace</hi> is equally <hi>ſafe,</hi> (though not equally <hi>comfortable</hi>) with the State of <hi>glory;</hi> and the Spiritual State of the <hi>weakeſt,</hi> equally <hi>ſafe</hi> (though not equally <hi>comfortable</hi>) with that of the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; <hi>ſalvation</hi> being annexed to a <hi>Real Vnion</hi> with Chriſt, which is grounded on the <hi>truth</hi> of Faith, not to <hi>comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Communion</hi> with him, which ordinarily attends the <hi>raiſed degrees,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> of Faith. Conclude we then all the Members (yea the very meaneſt) of the Church <hi>Inviſible</hi> to be (in this ſenſe) <hi>Invincible;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obeunt non pereunt,</note> 
               <hi>dye</hi> they muſt, <hi>periſh</hi> they ſhall not, cannot, — <hi>None of them is lost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is that <hi>Vnion</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> wherein all the Members of the Church-<hi>Catholick-Viſible,</hi> the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of the true Religion, throughout the world, are by vertue of their <hi>Common Profeſſion</hi> of <hi>One Lord, One Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph: 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>One Baptiſme,</hi> Goſpel-doctrine, and worſhip, united amongſt themſelves, and joyntly concorporated with Chriſt, as One Entire <hi>Body Catholick.</hi> Now to apply this to our purpoſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Vnion</hi> that is between Chriſt and the <hi>Catholick Viſible</hi>-Church, conſidered as a <hi>Collective</hi> Body of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, is alſo <hi>un-interruptible,</hi> admits of no <hi>breach:</hi> She (in this ſenſe) can neither, by Univerſal Apoſtacy, <hi>fall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63806:5"/>off,</hi> nor by any Violence, be <hi>broken off</hi> from her <hi>Common Head,</hi> Chriſt. True, The Church hath her <hi>Moon-like</hi> waxings and weanings, <hi>gradual</hi> though not <hi>ſubſtantial Changes. SIONS Sun</hi> hath his <hi>Apogaeums,</hi> and <hi>Perigae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums:</hi> The <hi>Waters of the Sanctuary,</hi> their <hi>Reciprocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> they (often) <hi>ebb</hi> as well as <hi>flow;</hi> The Churches <hi>Glory</hi> is frequently (what by <hi>Inteſtine</hi> Corruptions and Diviſions, what by <hi>forreign</hi> Combinations againſt her, and <hi>Torrents</hi> of perſecution) clouded and eclipſed, inſomuch that an <hi>ICHABOD</hi> might often ſeem, beſt to become her whom (yet) her Lord hath dignified with this title of honour, <hi>Chriſt-Myſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Light</hi> of the Church (though often <hi>eclipſed</hi>) was never as yet <hi>extinguiſhed;</hi> being continually renewed by the <hi>Auxiliary</hi> influences of the great <hi>Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Truth</hi> hath in no age wanted either <hi>Patron</hi> or <hi>Proſelyte.</hi> The <hi>Viſible</hi> Church ſurely was very <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive</hi> when the whole <hi>Body</hi> ſeemed to be contracted to one <hi>Member,</hi> abridged in a ſingle <hi>Elijah</hi> (that ſecond <hi>Jerub-baal,</hi> a <hi>Champion-Zealot</hi> for the Truth) and yet even then were there no leſs than 7000 <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 King 19.10.14.18. God had got their <hi>Hearts,</hi> and now <hi>Baal</hi> ſhall not ſo much as have a <hi>knee.</hi> Reflect we upon the Primitive Churches <hi>Sanguine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion</hi> under the Tyranny and ten Perſecutions of the <hi>Heatheniſh Heroes,</hi> when the whole earth was<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. in Pſa. 118. Vid. Corn. Tacit. <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Annal.</hi> Tertul. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. <hi>adverſ. Gent.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>purpled</hi> and <hi>ſcarleted</hi> with <hi>Martyr-blood:</hi> when the very <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> was a <hi>Crime,</hi> when he that profeſſed himſelf a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> dyed by a <hi>Sanguinary</hi> Law enacted to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, without either ſelf-defence or conviction; when thouſands were diſpatched being <hi>nominis tantum et ſectae rei,</hi> guilty of a meer name <hi>(Chriſtian).</hi> When <hi>Diocleſian</hi> that Infernal Wolf, (having upon a Hell-deviſed Oracle or Prophecy, <hi>viz:</hi> That if the Chriſtians were but once cut off, the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire would wonderfully flouriſh) cauſed no leſſe than 17000 to be maſſacred in one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63806:5"/>moneth) did moſt wickedly boaſt <hi>De delet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nomine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiano,</hi> That he had everlaſtingly raſed out of memory, and utterly aboliſhed the very <hi>name</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> yet could not the <hi>ſword</hi> of violence ever interſect the line of <hi>Church-Succeſſion;</hi> yea the more they were <hi>mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> down, the more they <hi>multiplyed; Plures efficimur, quoties metimur,</hi> ſaith that <hi>Chriſtian-Mecaenas,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi> adver. Geut.</note> 
               <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian.</hi> Againe, who could have expected any to have appeared for the patronage of the Truth, under the <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Zone</hi> of <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> perſecution? and yet behold even then, hath Chriſt his <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> Rev. 11. <hi>Two.</hi> though, <hi>but two;</hi> though the <hi>leaſt</hi> number, yet <hi>a number;</hi> though a <hi>ſmall,</hi> yet a <hi>competent</hi> number; a <hi>Quorum</hi> of Witneſſes, by whoſe teſtimony the oppoſed Truth ſhould be protected and eſtabliſhed; ſo impoſſible a thing it is that Chriſt ſhould ever be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without a Witneſſe.</hi> Call we to mind <hi>Modern</hi> Perſecutors, That <hi>Engliſh Lion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> Q. M. with her <hi>Wolf</hi> and <hi>Leopard, Brethren in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> Bloody <hi>Charis</hi> the <hi>fifth,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> both which <hi>died</hi> their ſouls <hi>red</hi> with <hi>blood,</hi> they having deſtroyed, of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> the one 50000 in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, the other 18000 in <hi>Belgia</hi> in ſix years time; the <hi>French Maſſacre Anno</hi> 1572. Even all the conflicts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>ſeed of the Woman,</hi> and the <hi>ſeed of the Serpent,</hi> ſince the quarrel was firſt begun in Paradiſe, which hath been fiercely purſued well nigh <hi>ſix thouſand years:</hi> All that time hath God <hi>uninterruptedly</hi> maintained a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued <hi>Series</hi> and <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of Perſons, (notwithſtanding <hi>Captivities</hi> and hoſtile <hi>Cruelties</hi>) <hi>Patriarks, Prophets,</hi> and all the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi>-Profeſſors; <hi>Apoſtles, Fathers, Councels, Confeſſors, Martyrs,</hi> and all <hi>New-Teſtament</hi>-Saints; in and by whom the true Religion, hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, preſerved, and (<hi>ſucceſſively</hi> though not alwayes very <hi>ſucceſſefully</hi>) propagated, <hi>kept</hi> by ſome, <hi>guarded</hi> by others, and (through good providence) <hi>tranſmitted,</hi> by all to us.<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.10.</note> 'Tis impoſſible that Chriſt ſhould want a <hi>Seed</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63806:6"/>(a Church) or that Church, a <hi>Guardian</hi> and <hi>Defendor of the Faith:</hi> For the Church to be <hi>Chriſt-leſſe,</hi> and for Chriſt to be <hi>Church-leſſe,</hi> are equall impoſſibilities. The Church Militant is Chriſts <hi>Sublunary</hi> Kingdom, which admits of no <hi>Interregna,</hi> or <hi>Vacancy:</hi> There is in her (though not an <hi>Infallibility</hi>) yet an <hi>Indeficiency;</hi> Subject ſhe is to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> within, but not to <hi>Interruption;</hi> to <hi>Obſtruction</hi> from without, but not to <hi>deſtruction.</hi> She is a houſe <hi>built upon a Rock,</hi> Mat. 16.18. and this <hi>Rock</hi> is Chriſt, (the <hi>Foundation,</hi> as well as <hi>Founder</hi> of his Church,) therefore ſhe muſt needs be Impregnable and Invincible; —<hi>The Gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile againſt her:</hi> A promiſe ever made good to the <hi>Whole Body</hi> of the <hi>Catholick-Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> as it is to every <hi>Individual Member</hi> of the <hi>Catholick-Inviſible</hi>-Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> which is between Chriſt and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Viſible</hi> Profeſſors and Churches, (parts of the Church <hi>Catholick-Viſible</hi>) may be <hi>broken</hi> and <hi>interrupted,</hi> is a truth that hath been verified in many ſad experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; foraſmuch as all are not <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that are called <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el:</hi> Many <hi>Particular</hi> Churches and <hi>Councels</hi> (however our Neighbours in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> amongſt the reſt of their <hi>Romiſh ſtrange-fire,</hi> aſcribe an <hi>Infallibility</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring</hi> Quality to them, yet) are known to have ſo far degenerated as to become inſtead of <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, Synagogues</hi> of <hi>Satan;</hi> witneſſe the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> (which (though once recorded for <hi>Golden Candleſticks,</hi> Rev. 2. yet) are at this day the Receptacles of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan</hi> Idolatry) <hi>Judea</hi> (that <hi>degenerate Vine</hi>) <hi>Rome</hi> (that <hi>Adulterate See</hi>) &amp;c. But this is not only <hi>Schiſm,</hi> but <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> being a <hi>degeneracy</hi> from the true <hi>Catholick-Apoſtolick</hi> Faith, and a <hi>Separation</hi> from, or, <hi>not holding of the head, from which all the body by joynts and bands having nouriſhment miniſtred, and knit together, increaſeth with the increaſe of God,</hi> (Col. 2.19.) which is inconſiſtent, not onely with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> but with the <hi>Verity</hi> and very <hi>Being</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63806:6"/>of a (true) Church; whence thoſe Churches are deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly called <hi>Apoſtatical,</hi> as well as <hi>Schiſmatical,</hi> and <hi>Renegadoes</hi> or <hi>Fugitives</hi> from the Faith of Chriſt, ſuch as <hi>Parphyrie, Julian,</hi> miſerable <hi>Spira,</hi> and ſuch like (who have of <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Profeſſed</hi> Members of the Body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Enemies to the Head, ſome of them turning open <hi>Perſecutors</hi> of that Faith whereof they were once <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi>) are not barely called <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> but branded for curſed <hi>Apoſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Communion</hi> wherein the Members of this great <hi>Corporation</hi> the Church <hi>Catholick-Viſible</hi> are by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their <hi>Common Profeſſion</hi> of the true Religion, and Faith of Chriſt, united one with another, is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to a twofold <hi>Schiſm</hi> or breach; viz: 1. A breach <hi>in</hi> the Church, and 2. A breach <hi>from</hi> the Church: The firſt conſiſts in <hi>Inteſtine Diviſions</hi> and <hi>differences,</hi> either 1. in point of <hi>Judgement,</hi> and that (principally) about matters either of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> or <hi>Worſhip</hi> (if the <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> be in a point <hi>fundamental</hi> or <hi>incorrigibly perſiſted</hi> in, it is then <hi>Hereſie,</hi> which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calls <hi>Schiſma in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteratum</hi>); or elſe 2. in point of <hi>Charity</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Love.</hi> The ſecond conſiſts in a <hi>degeneracy</hi> from the <hi>true Religien,</hi> and a <hi>voluntary relinquiſhing</hi> of a <hi>Church-ſtate</hi> but this is (as I have ſaid above of <hi>not holding of the Head</hi>) not <hi>Schiſme</hi> onely, but <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> a <hi>Cat holick</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Separation;</hi> for one that thus relinquiſheth Chriſts <hi>Body-Catholick,</hi> ſeparates from it, <hi>Tanquam Membrum ab Integro,</hi> as a <hi>Member</hi> from the <hi>Whole;</hi> now as a Leg or Arm, when loſt, ceaſeth to be a member of the body Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, to which it was united, even ſo a Profeſſor thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, ceaſeth, <hi>In ſtatu quo,</hi> (without recovery by repentance) to be a Member of this Body Myſticall. Whereas many are moſt juſtly condemned for <hi>Separatiſts</hi> (I ſhall not need to name any) who (yet) while they <hi>hold the Head,</hi> and profeſſedly <hi>own</hi> the <hi>Catholick-Apoſtolick</hi> Faith of Chriſt, cannot be <hi>diſowned</hi> for <hi>Members</hi> of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63806:7"/>
               <hi>Body, Branches</hi> in the <hi>Vine, Part</hi> of the <hi>Myſtical Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the <hi>Church Catholick-Viſible: Church-Communion</hi> is diſtinguiſhable into
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Real.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Peſonal.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>There is a <hi>Real Community,</hi> and a <hi>Perſonal Society:</hi> now though thoſe <hi>Separatiſts</hi> refuſe, by way of <hi>Perſonal Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> to communicate with that Church from which they ſeparate, yet they continue a <hi>Real Saint-Communion</hi> and <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with her in the Enjoyment of the ſame <hi>(Objective)</hi> Ordinances; <hi>Prayer, Word,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and therefore notwithſtanding their <hi>Separation</hi> from a <hi>Particular,</hi> they ceaſe not to be Members of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church; <hi>Real Community</hi> being maintained, though <hi>Perſonal Society</hi> be (unjuſtly) denyed.</p>
            <p>The Third <hi>Church-Vnion</hi> is that <hi>Social-Local-Joynt-Fellowſhip,</hi> wherein the Members of a <hi>Particular</hi> Church are united one with another, not only by the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the ſame Faith and Religion (all the Members of the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Vniverſal</hi> Church are thus united) but in the <hi>participation</hi> of the ſame Ordinances, Adminiſtrations, and inſtituted worſhip of Chriſt, in a <hi>particular</hi> place, where there is fitting opportunity of executing, and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due obſervance to Rules of <hi>Joynt-Communion;</hi> which is not a thing poſſible for the <hi>Vniverſal</hi> Church, <hi>now,</hi> through <hi>numeroſity</hi> and <hi>multitude;</hi> though once it was, viz: when the whole <hi>Catholick-Chriſtian</hi> Church conſiſted of about but 120. Members in all, Act. 1.15. Now</p>
            <p>This <hi>Comunion</hi> may admit of a twofold <hi>breach,</hi> viz. 1. <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the Church, 2. <hi>Separation</hi> from the Church (as the breach in the Church-<hi>Catholick</hi> before): The firſt is a breach either 1. in point of <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Opinion;</hi> or 2. in point of <hi>Charity</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Affection,</hi> (the too too frequent iſſue and reſult of the other) 'tis chiefely the former (I preſume) that Sr. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calls <hi>Diſſidium Congregationis, Church-diſſention;</hi> the latter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63806:7"/>he calls <hi>Odium Fraternum, Brother-hatred</hi> and <hi>diſ-affection;</hi> both ſad <hi>Church-Rents:</hi> What, when <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Abraham (Brethren)</hi> are at <hi>ſtrife,</hi> when <hi>Brethren fall out by the way!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Separation from</hi> the Church, is either
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Partial.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Total.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1. <hi>Negative.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Poſitive.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>Partial Separation;</hi> when we decline Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Church in ſome Ordinances, but joyn with her in others; as in <hi>Prayer,</hi> but not in <hi>hearing</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> or in both thoſe, but not in the <hi>Saerament.</hi> 2. A <hi>Total Separation</hi> is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> declenſion of Communion with a Church in every Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Negative Separation;</hi> when we withdraw from Communion with ſome Church, not joyning with any other, but continuing in hopes and expectation of the happy amendment of that Church from which we withdraw, with a purpoſe of <hi>returning</hi> to her when reformed. 2 <hi>Poſitive Separation;</hi> when we do not only decline Communion with a Church, but divide into ſeveral <hi>Parties, Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and new <hi>Conventions,</hi> as (probably) 'twas amongſt the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> One ſaying <hi>I am of Paul;</hi> another, <hi>I am of Apollo;</hi> a third, <hi>I am of Cephas, &amp;c.</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.) embodying in ſeveral Church-wayes, ſetting up <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar,</hi> and <hi>Threſhold</hi> againſt <hi>Threſhold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Separation</hi> from the Church, may be <hi>Culpable</hi> or <hi>Incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, Lawful</hi> or <hi>Vnlawful</hi> (and that more or leſſe) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its <hi>Grounds</hi> and <hi>Cauſes:</hi> Now the only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Grounds or Cauſes of a <hi>Total-Poſitive Separation,</hi> are uſually reckoned three, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Intolerable Perſecution</hi> from Perſons.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Damnable Hereſie</hi> in poynt of Doctrine.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Groſſe Idolatry</hi> in poynt of Worſhip.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are the Grounds of our juſt <hi>Departure</hi> from the <hi>Tyrannical, Heretical, Idololatrical,</hi> Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> O happy <hi>Divorce!</hi> may the Lord perpetuate it! that we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63806:8"/>may never <hi>ſay a Confederacy</hi> to her again,<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.12.</note> but upon Gods own <hi>Terms of Accommodation, — Let them return unto thee, but return not thou unto them,</hi> Jer. 15.19. Again, when the <hi>Corruptions</hi> of a Church are ſuch, as that one cannot communicate with her <hi>without ſin</hi> unavoydably; That ſeems to me, to be a juſt ground, though not of <hi>Poſitive,</hi> yet of <hi>Negative,</hi> though not of <hi>Total,</hi> yet of <hi>Partial, Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> and <hi>Non-Communion</hi> in ſuch a caſe, can be no <hi>ſin,</hi> therefore no <hi>Schiſm.</hi> How can <hi>Non-Communion</hi> be <hi>ſin,</hi> there, where one cannot communicate <hi>without ſin?</hi> unleſs men will <hi>impoſe</hi> or ſuffer to be <hi>impoſed</hi> upon themſelves, a <hi>Neceſſity of ſinning;</hi> that which true <hi>Piety</hi> abhorrs. I am not alone here, or without the ſuffrage of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-Learned, (a ſufficient protection againſt the brand of <hi>Novelty</hi>) who ſay that if a Church be either no <hi>true Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drey,</hi> in his Treatiſe Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency a great Schiſm.</hi>
               </note> or ſo extreamly <hi>corrupted,</hi> that a good Chriſtian cannot hold <hi>Communion</hi> with it, <hi>without ſin; Separation</hi> in that caſe is no <hi>Schiſm;</hi> but they are the <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> that give the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of that Separation: Then let the VVorld Judge who in <hi>England</hi> may moſt deſervedly be branded for <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the Contrary, <hi>Culpable, Faulty,</hi> and <hi>ſinful Separation</hi> from the Church (the <hi>Schiſm</hi> in queſtion) is (as I think it is generally deſcribed) <hi>a Cauſeleſs Separation from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with, and participation of Chriſts inſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in, a true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> This premiſed, we ſhall eaſily diſcover what <hi>Church-breach, Schiſm,</hi> or <hi>Separation,</hi> it is, that <hi>Mr. Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> chargeth upon thoſe in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (and amongſt thoſe my ſelf) who under the preſent Providence (though they joyn with her in the <hi>Inſtituted</hi> VVorſhip, and Subſtantial Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, therein admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by, as <hi>Prayer, Hearing of che Word Preached, Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pſalms,</hi> &amp;c. yet) do not, cannot, communicate with her, in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer;</hi> as being guilty of a <hi>ſinful Practice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63806:8"/>1. 'Tis not a <hi>breach</hi> of the firſt <hi>Vnion,</hi> viz. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Elect,</hi> Gods <hi>Choſen</hi> Ones, are by a <hi>true Faith</hi> or the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Faith <hi>un-interruptedly</hi> indwelling in them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned one with another, and all of them with their <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Head,</hi> Chriſt; for this (as is declared) is an utter <hi>Impoſſibility;</hi> which none but an <hi>Arminian</hi> Spirit will deny.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis not a <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Communion</hi> with the <hi>Catholick-Viſible</hi> Church, and her <hi>Common Head,</hi> Chriſt, by vertue of <hi>Outward Profeſſion,</hi> (which is called a <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Separation</hi>); for this were not only <hi>Schiſm</hi> but <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> (as hath been ſaid) not only a <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Church-Vnity</hi> but a <hi>Voluntary forfeiture</hi> of a <hi>Church-State;</hi> an Imputation which my <hi>Creed</hi> will acquit me from; while I profeſſedly own the true Catholick Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Apoſtles, the Orthodox Fathers, Councels, Confeſſors, Martyrs</hi> in all Ages, and the <hi>Reformed</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis not a <hi>Breach in</hi> the Church; either, 1. in poynt of <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Opinion;</hi> nor 2. in poynt of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Affection.</hi> 1. Not in poynt of <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Opinion;</hi> for, as for <hi>Erroneous</hi> Principles, according to that light God hath given me, I abhor them: <hi>Church-rending Diviſions,</hi> I ſhall not willingly or wittingly be acceſſory to; never forgeting (what <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of <hi>Caſpar Schwenckfield</hi>) that <hi>Church-Incendiaries</hi> may kindle a fire here, which may burn themſelves to all eternity, hereafter; But if a <hi>Diſſent</hi> in <hi>Judgment</hi> about matters of <hi>Worſhip</hi> or <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> (yea and (perchance) in <hi>Doctrinal</hi> poynts too, at leaſt <hi>Non-Fundamentals</hi>) from our preſent <hi>Church-Pilots,</hi> be a <hi>Schiſm,</hi> I ſhall not buſie my ſelf about either Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or Excuſe, under the Cenſure; but ſure I am, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> himſelf is in this ſenſe a <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> or elſe juſtly may he be branded for an <hi>Apoſtate.</hi> 2. Nor in poynt of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Affection:</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is no competent Arbitrator in that caſe; God himſelf is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63806:9"/>beſt able to judge, who at this day <hi>walks charitably,</hi> who not: for my own part, I have Charity for all <hi>Church-Members,</hi> (underſtand their <hi>Perſons,</hi> not their <hi>Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>); The Law of <hi>Piety,</hi> and the Law of <hi>Charity</hi> God himſelf hath married together, and <hi>whom God hath joyned, let no man ſeparate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Breach</hi> or <hi>Schiſm</hi> (then) charged, muſt be a <hi>Separation</hi> from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> not 1, <hi>Total,</hi> ſince I communicate with her in thoſe Parts of Chriſts inſtituted Worſhip and Ordinances, <hi>Prayer, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c. Nor 2. <hi>Poſitive,</hi> whilſt I turn not <hi>Conventicler,</hi> and embody not into a <hi>Party</hi> or <hi>Convention</hi> ſet up againſt her, <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar, Threſhold</hi> againſt <hi>Threſhold,</hi> &amp;c. But 1. <hi>Partial,</hi> and 2. <hi>Negative,</hi> viz: meer <hi>Non-Communion</hi> with her in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> or ſtinted and <hi>Set-Forms</hi> of <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> This is the <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> charged, This is the <hi>Crime</hi> and great <hi>Article of Endictment.</hi> What, and is Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> turned <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Two Things I equally diſlike, <hi>Separation</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Superſtition</hi> on the other, (and what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Chriſtian will not?) they being deſtructive, the one to the <hi>Vnity,</hi> the other to the <hi>Purity</hi> of the Church) and the latter not more than the former, (underſtand I pray you <hi>ſinfull Separaiotn</hi>); <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> is a <hi>Rent</hi> and <hi>Wound</hi> in Chriſts <hi>Body,</hi> a <hi>Crucifying afreſh of the Son of God:</hi> The <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> Rendings of the Church by <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and ſuch like Fanaticks in <hi>Germany,</hi> coſt Zealous <hi>Luther</hi> no little grief and lamentation. God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give thoſe who are known to have been too too guilty of ſuch <hi>Sectarian-Cruelty</hi> here at home:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.13. Zech. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>Is Chriſt divided?</hi> was a ſad <hi>Interrogatory:</hi> What, Chriſt <hi>wounded in the houſe of</hi> his <hi>friends!</hi> that's ſad! The <hi>Voluntary Rending</hi> of <hi>Chriſt-Myſtical</hi> is a ſin, nothing inferiour (in my mind) to that of the <hi>Jews Crucifying</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63806:9"/>foraſmuch as that it reacheth both Head and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>That then which inclineth me to this attempt is, not Conſciouſneſſe to my ſelf of any <hi>Schiſm</hi> or <hi>(ſinfull) Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> (though I perceive you are ready to eſpouſe mine Acculers quarrel in caſe of non-ſatisfaction to your enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced requeſt) but the prevalent ſenſe as well of your <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity,</hi> as of mine own <hi>innocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Epiſtle</hi> (poſſibly) may ſeem to be with the City of <hi>Myndus,</hi> lyable to upbraiding, the Porch being too big, but neither is the premiſed Introduction larger, nor the ſubſequent diſcourſe more brief, than (I judged) expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Grounds and Reaſons, urged for <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in all Acts of worſhip (and conſequently in <hi>Common-Prayer</hi>) therein adminiſtred by; and againſt <hi>Separation</hi> or withdrawment from the ſame; are all reduced to four <hi>Poſitions,</hi> or <hi>Argumentative Propoſitions;</hi> from which <hi>(Premiſes)</hi> he infers, partly the <hi>Lawfulneſs,</hi> partly the <hi>Expediency,</hi> and partly the indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of the former, as the <hi>ſinfulneſſe</hi> and <hi>unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantableneſſe,</hi> (the <hi>Schiſm</hi>) of the latter: And thoſe <hi>Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> he calls CONSIDERATIONS, which come now to be <hi>conſidered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONSID. 1.<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> 
               <hi>Communion with the Church-Viſible in all the Acts</hi> (I had rather ſay <hi>Parts</hi>) <hi>of Solemn Publique Worſhip, is an Eſſential part of the ſanctification of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, or Lords day, and poſitive indiſpenſable duty of every particular ſoul, called by the name of God,</hi> to be onely <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded</hi> by a <hi>reall inevitable neceſſity,</hi> with aſſurance to any, that <hi>God will have mercy, and not ſacrifice.</hi> This is the <hi>Major-Propoſition</hi> of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> great <hi>Doom-Argument.</hi> The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> muſt be this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Communion with the Church of England in her Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy or Common-Prayer</hi> (commonly called, <hi>Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi>)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63806:10"/>
               <hi>is Communion with the Church-Viſible, in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and Publique Worſhip:</hi> and then the Concluſion muſt be,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore Communion with the Church of England in her Liturgy and Common-Prayer, is an Eſſential part of the ſanctification of the Sabbath, or Lords day, and a poſitive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable duty,</hi> &amp;c. and by conſequence <hi>Non-Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp;c. muſt be a breach of duty, and therefore, a <hi>ſin,</hi> viz: <hi>SCHISM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>REMONS. <hi>Honoured Friend,</hi> My Anſwer to this, ſhall be threefold. Viz:
<list>
                  <item>1. By way of <hi>Conceſſion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By way of <hi>Diſtinction.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. By way of <hi>Retortion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of <hi>Conceſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Church of <hi>England</hi> (That is the <hi>Community of Chriſtians in this Nation, concorporated by Baptiſm, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the true God and Jeſus Chriſt, and ſubjected to the Word and Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c.) is a <hi>true Church,</hi> cannot in juſtice be denyed; Her <hi>Primitive Conſtitution</hi> being by Hiſtory (<hi>Times Index,</hi> and our beſt <hi>Intelligencer</hi> touching Antiquity) known to have been <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> adminiſters to me no occaſion of doubt in the thing: But whoever were the <hi>Seminary Founders</hi> thereof, (whether <hi>Simon Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotes,</hi> or <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> (Chriſts <hi>Immediate Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>) or <hi>Ariſtobolus,</hi> or <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the <hi>Monk,</hi>) 'tis no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Faith; only let none <hi>deſpiſe-his Birth-right,</hi> as <hi>Eſau</hi> did his. O what a happineſſe is it that our <hi>Native</hi> Land ſhould be a (thus) <hi>Conſecrated Soil;</hi> and that we ſhould be by <hi>birth</hi> (in this reſpect) <hi>Sons of the Church, (Viſible Church Members:)</hi> The Inroades of <hi>Popery</hi> into this <hi>Iland,</hi> ſince the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſſe</hi> firſt <hi>roſe</hi> herein, have been both various and violent, (and what they may further be, God knows) but God hath ſafe-kept his <hi>Engliſh-Ark</hi> in the midſt of that <hi>Deluge;</hi> the <hi>Rock of Ages,</hi> hath hitherto been her <hi>Ararat;</hi> By no <hi>Antichriſtian Inundations,</hi> was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63806:10"/>ſhe ever as yet (totally) overwhelmed; <hi>Popery</hi> ſpoiled her <hi>Beauty,</hi> but did not deſtroy her <hi>Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> turning <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> hath acknowledged this Churches <hi>(preſent) Corruptions</hi> as well in <hi>Things</hi> (viz: <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> therein adminiſtrable by) as in <hi>Perſons,</hi> both <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>People, Viſible Members,</hi> (the <hi>Integral</hi> Parts thereof): But a <hi>True</hi> Church is one thing, a <hi>Pure</hi> Church another; Here is the <hi>New-Creature,</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after (onely) the <hi>Pure-Creature.</hi> Now the queſtion is not about <hi>Church-purity,</hi> (alas! <hi>Adulterate Mixtures</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, are a too too plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of this <hi>now</hi>) but <hi>Church-Entity,</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Being</hi> of the Church, (which our <hi>Engliſh Donatiſts</hi> (Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> may know whom I mean) having (formerly) well nigh confounded, did (like their <hi>Progenitors</hi>) moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledgiouſly <hi>monopolize</hi> the Church of Chriſt in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, confining the <hi>Formality</hi> (and therefore the <hi>Truth</hi> and very <hi>Eſſence</hi>) of a Church, within the narrow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of their <hi>Confederate</hi> Members, as if it had not been poſſible, for their <hi>Ark</hi> to contain a <hi>Cham,</hi> or for <hi>Tares</hi> to grow within their <hi>Incloſure;</hi> (God will I hope, humble them for it). <hi>Truth,</hi> we muſt needs aſcribe to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> while She profeſſedly owns the <hi>Faith</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>True Religion:</hi> For the <hi>Truth</hi> of Religion proves the <hi>Entity</hi> (or <hi>Being</hi>), as the <hi>Power</hi> of Religion the <hi>Purity</hi> of a Church: while She <hi>owns</hi> the <hi>Head,</hi> ſhe muſt not be <hi>diſowned</hi> for a Part of the <hi>Body</hi> (the Church <hi>Catholick-Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi>); while She <hi>ſeparates</hi> not from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we have no warrant (<hi>totally</hi> and <hi>poſitively</hi>) to <hi>ſeparate</hi> from <hi>Her:</hi> She may be Chriſts <hi>Spouſe</hi> (viz: <hi>Viſibly</hi> and <hi>Profeſſedly</hi>) though not a <hi>Chaſt-Virgin</hi>-Spouſe; a <hi>Wife,</hi> though an <hi>Adultereſſe;</hi> retaining her <hi>Affinity,</hi> though not her <hi>Virginity. Corruptions</hi> in the Church are either</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Perſonal.</hi> or 2. <hi>Real.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63806:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Real,</hi> again, either or
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Subſtantial</hi> and <hi>Intrinſecal.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Circumſtantial</hi> and <hi>Extrinſecal.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The latter is Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own diſtinction (though poſſibly he and I may differ in the application of it).</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perſonal Corruptions</hi> in <hi>Scandalous Profeſſors,</hi> or <hi>Viſible</hi> Church-<hi>Members,</hi> (<hi>Miniſters</hi> (as well as others) the <hi>Hophnie's</hi> and <hi>Phinehas's</hi> of our age) <hi>defile</hi> a Church: <hi>Corruptions Objective</hi> and <hi>Real,</hi> though onely <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial</hi> and <hi>Extrinſecal,</hi> (in <hi>Outward Rites</hi> and <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> or corrupt <hi>Modes</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> of Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the <hi>Antiquated Jewiſh Veſtments, Croſſe</hi> in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, <hi>Kneeling</hi> at the <hi>Supper,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>adulterate</hi> a Church. <hi>Corruptions Subſtantial</hi> and <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> (which are <hi>Church-waſting</hi> Corruptions; the very <hi>Vitals</hi> and <hi>Intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals</hi> of Religion, being by them deſtroyed) do <hi>(ipſo facto,)</hi> actually <hi>divorce</hi> a Church from Chriſt; thoſe are the ſteps of Church-Apoſtacy, when the <hi>Wife</hi> becomes a <hi>Lewd-Woman;</hi> (<hi>Single Fornication</hi> in the firſt; <hi>Adultery</hi> in the ſecond; A <hi>Bill of Divorce</hi> in the laſt:) The Church of <hi>England</hi> is too truly chargeable with the two firſt, but not with the laſt, as is the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe having not (as yet, I pray God ſhe never may) with her degenerated from a <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> into an <hi>Antichriſtian See;</hi> nor her Members with <hi>hers,</hi> from <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors</hi> to <hi>Perſecutors</hi> of the Faith, not <hi>holding the True Head,</hi> but ſetting up ANOTHER NAME; being in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> (damnably) <hi>Heretical;</hi> in <hi>Worſhip</hi> (groſſely) <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous;</hi> in both <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi> The <hi>Eſſentials Conſtitutive</hi> of a <hi>True Church,</hi> are 1. the <hi>Head;</hi> 2. the <hi>Body;</hi> 3. the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> that is between them: which three concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the Church of <hi>England; Chriſt</hi> being her profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Head,</hi> ſhe being Chriſts profeſſed <hi>Body,</hi> and the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick-Faith</hi> being the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion-Bond</hi> whereby they are coupled together; She cannot in juſtice be denyed to be a <hi>True</hi> (though the Lord knows, far from a <hi>Pure</hi>) Church. <hi>Vid.</hi> Jun. <hi>lib. de Eccleſia.</hi> Herein I agree with Mr. <hi>Crofton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63806:11"/>2. By way of <hi>Diſtinction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things are here to be diſtinguiſhed; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Communion with the Church-Viſible.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Solemn and Publick Worſhip.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. There is a twofold <hi>Communion; viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>One by <hi>Profeſſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another by <hi>Participation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Church-Communion</hi> by way of Common <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the ſame true Religion, Faith, Doctrine, and inſtitured worſhip of Chriſt, (by vertue whereof all the Members of the Church-<hi>Catholick Viſible</hi> throughout the World, are concorporated and embodyed, one with another, and all of them with Chriſt as a <hi>Publick Head, Catholick Faith</hi> being the ground of <hi>Catholick Communion,</hi> the main <hi>Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the great <hi>Body Myſtical</hi>) is not only a <hi>Duty,</hi> but a <hi>Priviledge</hi> too, indiſpenſably neceſſary to ſalvation. <hi>Extra Eccleſiam nulla ſalus,</hi> is a ſevere <hi>Maxim</hi> not more known then true; no <hi>Salvation</hi> (ordinarily) without the <hi>Churches Line of Communication.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> is Gods <hi>Incloſure,</hi> (<hi>Cant.</hi> 9.12.) his <hi>Nurſery</hi> planted with the <hi>Trees of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> without whoſe <hi>Pale</hi> and <hi>Boundaries</hi> all that <hi>die</hi> doe <hi>periſh:</hi> Ah, <hi>my Dear Friend,</hi> Let me rather be a <hi>Myrtle</hi> in the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> then a <hi>Cedar</hi> in the <hi>Forreſt.</hi> 'Twere better <hi>England</hi> ſhould be <hi>unpeopled</hi> then <hi>unchur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched:</hi> A <hi>Church-leſſe</hi> People is a <hi>Chriſt-leſſe</hi> People; and if <hi>Chriſt-leſſe</hi> then <hi>Hope-leſſe,</hi> Epheſ. 2.12. <hi>Chriſt is the Head of the Body the Church,</hi> Coll. 1.18. No <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with this <hi>Head</hi> without <hi>Communion</hi> with this <hi>Body:</hi> Chriſt muſt be <hi>profeſſed,</hi> or (elſe) never <hi>poſſeſſed;</hi> no <hi>Saint-State</hi> without a <hi>Church-State;</hi> no Call by the <hi>Spirit</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Call by the <hi>Word</hi> firſt; ſo that no <hi>Word,</hi> no <hi>Life:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.13, 14.</note> — <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved; — Worſhip</hi> is neceſſary to <hi>Salvation: — How ſhall they call on him, in whom they have not beleeved? Faith</hi> is neceſſary to <hi>Worſhip: — How ſhall they beleeve in him, of whom they have not heard? Hearing</hi> is neceſſary
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63806:12"/>to <hi>Faith: — How ſhall they hear without a Preacher? Preaching</hi> is neceſſary to <hi>Hearing:</hi> ſo that, without <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> there is no <hi>Salvation;</hi> without <hi>Faith,</hi> no (true) <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> without <hi>Hearing,</hi> no <hi>Faith;</hi> and without <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> no <hi>Hearing;</hi> therefore <hi>(a primo ad ultimum)</hi> the <hi>Word preached</hi> is neceſſary to <hi>Salvation;</hi> — no <hi>Word,</hi> no <hi>Life;</hi> (ah! may this (loathed) <hi>Manna</hi> never fail from amidſt our <hi>Brittiſh-Iſrael!</hi>) Thrice miſerable are they whoſe <hi>Sun ſets,</hi> where the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſſe</hi> never <hi>roſe, — with healing in his Wings. Solomon</hi> (the great <hi>Sophi</hi> of the World) hath long agoe read the Deſtinie of ſuch; <hi>Where there is no Viſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eunt pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> 
               <hi>the people periſh,</hi> Prov. 29.18. a ſad <hi>Exit!</hi> There is <hi>Viſio Salvifica</hi> in the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, as well as <hi>Viſio Beatifica,</hi> in the Triumphant: There be no true <hi>Saints</hi> who are not (in this ſenſe) <hi>SEERS.</hi> This is the firſt <hi>Communion,</hi> wherein I am chargeable with no <hi>Breach,</hi> while I profeſſe my ſelf a <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> All <hi>Profeſſors</hi> throughout the VVorld, are in this reſpect <hi>Communicants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church <hi>Viſible,</hi> by way of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation,</hi> or actual <hi>Enjoyment</hi> of the Ordinances, and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt in a particular place (the <hi>Communion</hi> in queſtion) is (I grant) a <hi>Duty</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieging <hi>ſemper,</hi> but not <hi>ad ſemper:</hi> To explaine my ſelf; A <hi>Particular</hi> Church (ſuch as is the Church of <hi>England</hi>) having her riſe (as ſuch) not from a <hi>Common</hi> Call by the <hi>Word</hi> onely, (for the <hi>Catholick-Viſible</hi> Church hath her riſe from that) but from a <hi>Particular Providential</hi> Call, (for ſo I may term it) whereby Perſons (whether <hi>Natives</hi> or <hi>Forreigners</hi>), are called to inhabit, reſide, or live, there, where there is fit <hi>Opportunity</hi> of enjoying the Publique Ordinances, and celebrating the inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt by way of <hi>Social-Joynt-Communion;</hi> as <hi>Providence, Opportunity,</hi> or <hi>neceſſary Occaſions,</hi> ſhall vary, the <hi>Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to <hi>Joynt-Communion</hi> muſt vary alſo. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny that there may be many Members of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63806:12"/>Catholick,</hi> who (yet) never had opportunity of aſſociating themſelves with, or of <hi>Joynt-Communion</hi> in the <hi>Solemn Publique Worſhip</hi> he ſpeaks of, in a <hi>Particular</hi> Church; and many have had it, who have been deprived of it, as <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Marriners,</hi> profeſſing the true Religion, who in purſuance of their Secular Callings, are diſtanced from a true <hi>Conſtituted</hi> Church, ſome of them living in <hi>Spaine,</hi> others in <hi>India,</hi> others in <hi>Turky,</hi> &amp;c. or ſuch as through <hi>ſickneſs</hi> are kept from the Enjoyment of Publick Ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We cannot ſay that <hi>Communion</hi> with a <hi>Particular</hi> Church, in ſuch Perſons under that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence is an <hi>Indiſpenſable duty,</hi> or <hi>Non-Communion, Schiſm,</hi> unleſs we alſo ſay (which were very hard) that they are bound to an <hi>Impoſſibility; Providence</hi> gives a <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> (as it were) in caſe of <hi>Neceſſary</hi> and <hi>Inevitable Non-Communion:</hi> In a word, Where <hi>Opportunity</hi> is ſerving, <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> not obſtructing, <hi>Corruptions</hi> not barring, no <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> hindering, there <hi>Joynt-Communion</hi> in <hi>Solemn Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Worſhip</hi> is an <hi>Indiſpenſable duty;</hi> otherwiſe, That which gives a <hi>Call,</hi> gives alſo a <hi>Diſcharge,</hi> viz. <hi>Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that diſclaim all <hi>Church-Fellowſhip</hi> out of a pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh petulancy, ſlighting all opportunities thereof, are juſtly to be diſclaimed as <hi>Self-out-lawed;</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Seekers,</hi> &amp;c. led by the <hi>Ignis Fatuus,</hi> the <hi>wild-fire</hi> of their own deluded Fancy: Surely <hi>Communion of Saints</hi> is no Article of their <hi>Creed,</hi> the maintaining of which ſhould be in our reſpective Capacities, every ones endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. But to proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I own an Obligation lying upon me, whereby I am bound to communicate with the Church of <hi>England</hi> (whereof I profeſſe my ſelf a Member) ſhe being (as is acknowledged) a <hi>True</hi> Church (notwithſtanding her many <hi>Corruptions,</hi>) in theſe Parts of Gods <hi>Real-Solemn, Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip,</hi> wherein <hi>Violent Impoſitions, Prevalent Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,</hi> or ſome or other <hi>Inevitable barrs</hi> neceſſitate not a <hi>withdrawment</hi> and <hi>Non-Communion;</hi> and if I ſhould
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63806:13"/>not, I ſhould greatly ſin. But what does this make for <hi>Communion</hi> with her in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer?</hi> Yes, (ſayes Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>) 'Tis an Act of <hi>Solemn Publick Worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore matter of duty: That is (next) to be tryed.</p>
            <p>The Second Thing to be diſtinguiſhed, is, <hi>Solemn Publick Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religious <hi>Worſhip</hi> may be ſaid to be <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> in reſpect of a threefold <hi>Community</hi> or <hi>Solemnity:</hi> viz:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Perſonal,</hi> In reſpect of <hi>Perſons</hi> worſhipping.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Local,</hi> In reſpect of the <hi>Place</hi> of worſhip.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Real,</hi> In reſpect of the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of worſhip.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Worſhip</hi> which is celebrated by a <hi>Plurality</hi> or <hi>Society</hi> of Perſons, whereſoever convented, is <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Publique</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Perſons;</hi> now our <hi>Engliſh Liturgy-Service</hi> may (I confeſs) in this reſpect paſſe for Worſhip <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Publique,</hi> and ſo may the <hi>Popiſh-Maſſe-Service</hi> too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>Worſhip</hi> (properly) is in reſpect of <hi>Place, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn</hi> and <hi>Publick;</hi> the particular <hi>Place</hi> whereof, as well as the <hi>Worſhip</hi> it ſelf is <hi>appointed</hi> of God: Now the <hi>Jewiſh Worſhip</hi> celebrated in the <hi>Temple</hi> &amp; <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> was in this reſpect (as ſhall appear by and by) the onely <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Publique Worſhip</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Worſhip,</hi> whereof <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Author</hi> as well as the <hi>Object;</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Rule,</hi> as well as the <hi>Matter;</hi> The <hi>Catholick-Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> That <hi>Worſhip</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> Himſelf (the Churches <hi>Lord-Regent</hi> and <hi>Law-giver</hi>) did <hi>appoint</hi> and <hi>inſtitute;</hi> which the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> (His <hi>Seminary Diſciples</hi>) did, by vertue of Authority derived from Him, <hi>commend</hi> and <hi>command;</hi> which the <hi>Goſpel</hi> (the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches <hi>Directory</hi>) doth <hi>Licence</hi> and <hi>Warrant;</hi> which hath been by a <hi>Continued Series</hi> and <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of Chriſtian Profeſſors <hi>(Faiths Defenders)</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles, uninterruptedly</hi> maintained, and at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63806:13"/>length through the Current of <hi>Sixteen hundred</hi> years, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily (as to <hi>ſubſtance</hi> at leaſt) tranſmitted and conveyed to us, is in reſpect of <hi>Matter, Authentique Conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Reality,</hi> the onely <hi>Solemn Publique Divine Worſhip</hi> in the Chriſtian world. Now to apply.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Communion</hi> with the <hi>Church-Viſible</hi> in that <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which is in reſpect of <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Authentique Conſtitution, Solemn</hi> and <hi>Publique,</hi> namely, That which was inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt</hi> Himſelf, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>Publique Head;</hi> preached and preſſed by the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> the Churches <hi>Publique Guides;</hi> recorded (as the onely <hi>Evangelical Worſhip</hi>) in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>Publique Rule;</hi> and (in conformity to this Rule) obſerved and performed by the <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtians for the firſt <hi>two hundred</hi> years, the pureſt Ages of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, This and all other Churches <hi>Publique Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> is (I readily grant) an <hi>Eſſential Part of the Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Lords Day,</hi> and a <hi>Poſitive indiſpenſable duty,</hi> to be upon perill <hi>ſuperſeded</hi> or <hi>intermitted,</hi> upon no leſs Warrant or Authority then that which impoſed it, (with this aſſurance <hi>that God will have mercy, and not ſacrifice</hi>); In Conſcience whereof, I own my ſelf oblieged to joyn with ſome <hi>Society</hi> in a <hi>Particular (True)</hi> Church (a Part of the Church <hi>Catholick-Viſible</hi>) while <hi>opportunity</hi> ſerves, and no <hi>Real Inevitable Obſtruction</hi> hinders, in all the Parts of <hi>Real-Solemn-Publique</hi> Worſhip (<hi>Prayer, Praiſe,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Supper</hi>) wherein no <hi>Violent Impoſitions,</hi> nor any <hi>Real Impediment</hi> may bar but that I <hi>may</hi> communicate, nor <hi>Prevalent Corruptions</hi> neceſſitate a declenſion or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawment, but that I may <hi>without ſin.</hi> As <hi>Saint-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> is matter of <hi>Faith</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſo <hi>Joynt-Communion</hi> is <hi>(Caeteris Paribus</hi>) matter of <hi>Duty</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>); That which all the Profeſſed Members of this <hi>Spiritual Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> (the <hi>Church</hi>) are bound in their reſpective Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities to maintain: <hi>Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Joynt</hi>-endeavour of all, but ſo as that the <hi>purity</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63806:14"/>of the Church be alſo endeavoured, and (much more that) her <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Being,</hi> be not deſtroyed. I am no <hi>Divinorum Deſertor Caſtrorum</hi> (as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a (real) <hi>Separatiſt</hi>) no <hi>Camp-Fugitive</hi> or <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly-Forſaker;</hi> no, God knows I deteſt and diſown the Principles and Practiſes of ſuch as (wilfully and willingly, unneceſſarily and peeviſhly) <hi>forſake the aſſembling of themſelves together, as the manner of ſome</hi> (too too many in theſe late times) hath been in all Ages. There is a twofold <hi>Chriſtian Scope;</hi> one <hi>Primary,</hi> viz. <hi>Gods Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> the other <hi>Subordinate,</hi> viz. the Chriſtians <hi>Own Good.</hi> The <hi>Glory</hi> of God is or ought to be by a <hi>Goſpel-Law</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.) the <hi>Terminus Reductivus</hi> of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: To <hi>glorifie</hi> God is a <hi>Natural</hi> debt, due from the <hi>Man</hi> as well as from the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and from an <hi>Angel</hi> as well as from a <hi>Man;</hi> the whole Hoſt of Heaven are Gods <hi>Tributaries</hi> herein. The Chriſtians own <hi>Happineſſe</hi> is to be purſued next and in ſubordination to this. Now, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the <hi>Crown-Revenue</hi> of Heaven ſo much inhaunced, nor the <hi>Catholick</hi> Benefit of Chriſtians ſo much advanced, by <hi>Solitary Worſhip,</hi> as by the <hi>Joynt-Services</hi> of Profeſſors. 'Tis well worthy of our Obſervation, That Chriſt gave that <hi>Portion</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> of his <hi>Spirit</hi> to his Diſciples when <hi>aſſembled,</hi> which he never gave them whilſt <hi>apart,</hi> (the richeſt <hi>Donative</hi> that ever he beſtowed upon the Sons of Men!) <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4. great encouragement to Saints <hi>Joynt-Communion! Vis unita fortior.</hi> Now</p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Real-Solemn</hi> Worſhip and Indiſpenſable <hi>Joynt-Communion</hi> therein, is not confined to any one Particular place more then to another, under the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> not to <hi>Rome,</hi> more then to <hi>England,</hi> nor to a <hi>Cathedral</hi> more then to any other <hi>Church;</hi> nor to any <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Chappel,</hi> or any ſuch <hi>Fabrick</hi> and <hi>Structure</hi> in the World, more then to the <hi>open Fields;</hi> nor to a <hi>Publique,</hi> more then to a <hi>Private</hi> houſe, in it ſelf: The houſe of an <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> may receive this <hi>Ark:</hi> The Churches <hi>Chamber-Worſhip</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63806:14"/>(Act. 1.15.) was true <hi>Solemn Worſhip.</hi> My Friend, meer Conſcience of the Truth conſtrains me to ſpeak: They miſerably erre, who reſtrict the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>reality</hi> of <hi>Solemn</hi> Worſhip to a <hi>Publique</hi> place, a material <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Structure</hi> (which yet none that I know, but a few pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh <hi>Sectaries</hi> can diſlike) as if <hi>Locality,</hi> which is but a meer <hi>natural</hi> Circumſtance, were <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> or <hi>Eſſential</hi> to <hi>Goſpel Worſhip:</hi> And what if thoſe <hi>Places</hi> thould chance in proceſſe of time to become the Receptacles of <hi>Jewiſh, Popiſh, Idolatry?</hi> where would their <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Publique Worſhip</hi> then be? But (more <hi>Argumentatively</hi>) where were <hi>Material Temples</hi> or <hi>Churches</hi> in the dayes of the Apoſtles (other then that of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the <hi>Jewiſh Synagogues</hi>)? where were they for the <hi>firſt hundred</hi> and <hi>fifty</hi> years after Chriſt? when Chriſtians did celebrate their worſhip in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the <hi>Burial Places</hi> of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> (whence (probably) 'twas that their places of Aſſembly were called <hi>Martyria,</hi> and the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem, Martyrium magnum</hi>); and this was the reaſon why <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Emperors</hi> made it their firſt buſineſſe and care to barr and baniſh the Chriſtians from thoſe places: yea,<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. cont. Valent.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us, that in his dayes (<hi>viz.</hi> about <hi>two hundred</hi> and <hi>ſixty</hi> years after Chriſt) the Chriſtians had no other <hi>Meeting-places</hi> (Churches) then <hi>ſimplices domes,</hi> poor deſpicable Cottages, which were (ſaith he) <hi>antris &amp; latebris quam Templis ſimiliores,</hi> more like unto Caves, or Corners, then Churches: And 'tis probable, that there was not a <hi>Material</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Church,</hi> till about or after the times of <hi>Evariſtus</hi> and <hi>Dyoniſius,</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> well nigh <hi>three hundred</hi> years after the birth of Chriſt; <hi>Parochial Diſtributions</hi> being begun by the one, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the other. <hi>Sir,</hi> you may pleaſe to conſult<note n="*" place="margin">De <hi>Rer. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</hi> lib. 4. c. 9. lib. 5. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Polidor Vergilius</hi> and<note n="†" place="margin">De Orig. Temp. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> (both expert and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Antiquaries</hi>) in the caſe. Now, were Chriſtians all that time, becauſe not <hi>Templers,</hi> therefore no true <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers?</hi> Was there no <hi>Solemn Publique</hi> Worſhip per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63806:15"/>for ſo many <hi>hundred</hi> years (the pureſt Ages of the Chriſtian Church)? But further; When I read of St. <hi>Paul Sermoning,</hi> of <hi>Lydia converted,</hi> and of <hi>Prayer wont to be made</hi> by a <hi>River-ſide,</hi> (Act. 16.13, 14.) Of St. <hi>Paul</hi> a private <hi>Houſe-Preacher eighteen moneths,</hi> and that in a houſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning to a <hi>Synagogue</hi> (<hi>Baſils</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Act. 18.7.11.) Of St. <hi>Paul</hi> and his Followers, their <hi>Chamber-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> in the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Supper,</hi> (doubtleſs there was <hi>Prayer</hi> there too, Act. 20.7, 8.) When I read of the whole <hi>Catholick</hi> Chriſtian Church (a <hi>Conventicle</hi> conſiſting of about 120 Perſons) convented &amp; worſhipping in a <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateroom</hi> (Act. 1.15.) I am ſufficiently warranted ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to condemn all ſuch as limit <hi>Solemn Worſhip</hi> to any <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular place,</hi> as if its <hi>Solemnity</hi> conſiſted in its <hi>Locality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewiſh Worſhip</hi> was the onely <hi>Worſhip</hi> that ever could be called <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Publique</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Place;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> himſelf (not <hi>Men</hi> like our ſelves) determined upon the <hi>Place</hi> as well as the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of his worſhip in the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> which he did not in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church; the <hi>Jewiſh Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Oblations</hi> being limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firſt to the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and after that to the <hi>Temple;</hi> the former whereof was built according to Gods own <hi>Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Plat-form,</hi> namely, the <hi>Pattern ſhewed to Moſes</hi> upon the <hi>Mount;</hi> the latter was Gods own <hi>Choice</hi> (Deut. 12.5.11. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.29. 2 Chron. 7.12.) by <hi>Solomon</hi> through <hi>Divine Inſtinct dedicated</hi> to him, and by a miraculous Signal of favour and acceptance (2 Chron. 5.13, 14.) <hi>owned</hi> by him; and thus 'twas ſaid, <hi>In Jeruſalem is the place where men ought to worſhip,</hi> John 4.20. So that the <hi>Place</hi> of worſhip, was indeed a <hi>Part</hi> of worſhip, not onely a <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> but of the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of worſhip, amongſt the <hi>Jews;</hi> God having ſtampt <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Sacred Solemnity</hi> thereupon, (Mr.<note n="*" place="margin">Altar Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. <hi>page 77.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Crofton</hi> himſelf bearing me witneſſe.) But under the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> and in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, <hi>Locality</hi> is a meer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Indifferency; Local Liberty</hi> being a great part
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63806:15"/>of <hi>Evangelical Liberty,</hi> Mal. 1.11. Mat. 18.20. John 4.21, 24. Act. 10.35. 1 Tim. 2.8. Chriſt having <hi>Ore &amp; Corp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</hi> both as <hi>Man,</hi> and as <hi>Prophet,</hi> by his <hi>Preaching,</hi> as well as by his <hi>Coming</hi> aboliſhed <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Peculiarity</hi> (as of <hi>Time,</hi> ſo) of <hi>Place;</hi> the <hi>Typical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Tabernacle</hi> ceaſing in him as <hi>Antitype,</hi> and <hi>Local Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> being preached by him as <hi>Prophet,</hi> John 4.21. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that <hi>Two or Three</hi> (whereſoever) met in his <hi>Name,</hi> have the Solemn promiſe of his <hi>preſence</hi> (now) Mat. 18.20.) whereas if the <hi>Solemnity</hi> of his worſhip were tied to any one place, his <hi>preſence</hi> and the <hi>Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant bleſſing</hi> of his worſhip ſhould be tied to that place alſo. Who would have thought that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. lib. 3.</hi> De Cultu Sanctorum.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> that great Light of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Firmament, (the chief <hi>Atlas</hi> of that <hi>Orbe</hi>) ſhould have been ſo much in the dark, as to think that, <hi>Prayer,</hi> or (any other part of worſhip, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a <hi>Material Church,</hi> &amp;c. is of more <hi>Efficacy,</hi> then if it were celebrated elſewhere? as if Stone and Timber did contribure vertue to our devotion; or <hi>Prayers Efficacy</hi> depended on <hi>Locality!</hi> I wiſh there be not many <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> in this reſpect, fooliſh <hi>Superſtionaries!</hi> that cry, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer.7.4.</note> &amp;c. like their ſilly, blind <hi>Phariſaical</hi> Progenitors. But <hi>Sir,</hi> You and I are taught of God, aſſured by <hi>Holy Record,</hi> that <hi>Prayer,</hi> or any other part of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> in what place ſoever performed, will be accepted of God, through Chriſt, ſo he be but worſhipped according to his own <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> viz. — <hi>In Spirit, and in Truth,</hi> John 4.24. Let none then preſently conclude from a neceſſary declenſion of <hi>Local Society</hi> in a <hi>Publique place,</hi> a breach of <hi>Real Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> in <hi>True Solemn Publique Worſhip,</hi> which may (indeed) be maintained in any place indifferently. Yet</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church of <hi>England</hi> (while ſhe <hi>holds the Head</hi> (Chriſt) and profeſſeth the <hi>True Religion,</hi>) being a <hi>True</hi> Church (a Part of the Church <hi>Catholick-Viſible</hi>) as is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged: and a <hi>Publique Place,</hi> being dictated by the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63806:16"/>light of nature, and judged by men (to whoſe <hi>Prudential Determination</hi> the <hi>Conveniency</hi> or <hi>Inconveniency</hi> of <hi>Place</hi> of worſhip, as a <hi>Natural</hi> Circumſtance, is left, though it be a meer matter of <hi>Indifferency</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and in it <hi>ſelf</hi>) to be fitteſt for <hi>Publique Joynt-Communion,</hi> and therefore (though not <hi>ſanctified</hi>) yet prudentially <hi>ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred</hi> and devoted thereunto; I muſt needs own my ſelf called to communicate (and in anſwer to that call I do communicate) with <hi>her,</hi> and that, in the Place of <hi>Publique Aſſembly,</hi> in all the Parts of <hi>Real-Solemn Divine</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, wherein I may without either <hi>let</hi> or <hi>ſin.</hi> And thus <hi>Sir,</hi> 'tis my known Practice (which you are no ſtranger to) to joyn with the preſent Aſſemblies in <hi>Prayer,</hi> (though not their <hi>Common-Prayer</hi>) <hi>Praiſe,</hi> or <hi>Singing of Pſalms, Hearing of the Word,</hi> all which are Subſtantial parts of <hi>True Solemn Divine Worſhip;</hi> what? and yet a <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt?</hi> Judge how little I deſerve that name, while this is my practice, and I exhort you and others to the like; Onely give me leave to tell you, that what was Reverend <hi>Beda's</hi> advice to him that ſhould chance to <hi>read</hi> the Books of that Heretical Biſhop <hi>Julian,</hi> I deſire (and it may be ſo will you) to improve in the <hi>hearing</hi> of ours,—<hi>Ita carpat botrum ut ſpinane caveat,</hi> Take of the <hi>Cluſter,</hi> but beware of <hi>Prickles,</hi> be ſure they be of <hi>Canaans</hi> Grapes; I would not willingly be <hi>ſtarved,</hi> but God keep me from being <hi>poyſoned;</hi> Take heed of <hi>Choaking, chew</hi> before you <hi>ſwallow;</hi> a <hi>Proſelyting Romaniſt</hi> (a <hi>Seminary Prieſt</hi>) will tell you otherwiſe; once ſwallow <hi>his</hi> Churches <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> and any thing will go down then; there is no room left for diſpute more, no need of the true <hi>Ballance of the Sanctuary.</hi> But I have not as yet laid finger upon the ſoar; therefore conſider,</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Church of <hi>Englands Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> (the great apple of <hi>ſtrife,</hi> &amp;c.) is a Part of this <hi>Real-Solemn</hi> worſhip of God, and that <hi>Communion</hi> with her therein (the thing urged) is (therefore) a <hi>Poſitive Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63806:16"/>duty,</hi> I muſt take leave (at leaſt till I ſee more cogent Arguments for it then have as yet been pleaded by the beſt that ever undertook the patronage of it) utterly to <hi>deny.</hi> This I know would ſeem ſtrange to many, (what, a <hi>Convocation-Maſter-piece!</hi> the <hi>Summum quod ſic</hi> of the <hi>Wit of men and Angels!</hi> the <hi>Monopoly</hi> of <hi>Divine Service!</hi> the <hi>Prayers of the Church!</hi> &amp;c. and yet no Part of <hi>True Solemn Worſhip!</hi>) but that it is written for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſatisfaction, and by way of private Apology. <hi>Sir,</hi> 'tis a fixed Principle with me, which I ſhould not fear to publiſh to the world, (had my tongue the liberty of mine Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers in the caſe, <hi>viz.</hi>) That there is no <hi>True Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> whereof <hi>God</hi> is not the <hi>Author</hi> as well as the <hi>Object,</hi> the <hi>Alpha</hi> as well as the <hi>Omega:</hi> What is not <hi>Inſtituted</hi> Worſhip, is none of <hi>His</hi> Worſhip, but meer <hi>Will-Worſhip,</hi> for God will be worſhipped <hi>Deſuo,</hi> his Soul loathing all that <hi>Service</hi> (though (poſſibly) nick-named <hi>Divine,</hi>) wherein there is more of the <hi>Creature,</hi> than of <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> (more of <hi>Man</hi> than of <hi>God</hi>); What Reaſon either from <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Common Light,</hi> can perſwade me other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? Now, can Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſay <hi>Bona fide</hi> ('tis not a matter to be dallied withal) that <hi>Liturgies</hi> or <hi>ſtinted</hi> &amp; <hi>Set-Forms</hi> of Prayer, were ever <hi>Inſtituted</hi> by <hi>Chriſt, Practiſed</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtles, Intended</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> or obſerved by the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtian</hi> Church, in the beſt and pureſt ages after Chriſt, (whoſe <hi>Practice</hi> in the caſe was to be a <hi>Leading Caſe</hi> and an <hi>Imitable Example</hi> to all ſucceeding Churches) In a word, Can he prove <hi>Englands Common-Prayer</hi> part of Chriſts <hi>Inſtituted Worſhip?</hi> Let him produce <hi>Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> (either) <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Preſident</hi> for it, (which will be a hard matter for him to do) elſe ſurceaſe his cenſure; for what other can it be then a meer <hi>Humane Ordinance, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-erogatory Worſhip, Arbitrary Service,</hi> even <hi>Scripture-bitten Will-Worſhip,</hi> one of the (juſtly condemned) <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and Ordinances of men,</hi> Col. 2.22, 23. What is <hi>Will-Worſhip</hi> if this be not? Yea, but the <hi>Matter</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63806:17"/>of it is good, (this is the ordinary plea, but) ſo is a great part of the <hi>Popiſh Miſſal,</hi> (with which it ſo much ſymbolizeth, (eſpecially their <hi>Letany,</hi> the firſt <hi>Edition</hi> of <hi>ours</hi>); and ſo of the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran:</hi> But will that prove it a <hi>Divine Conſtitution?</hi> Now, the Queſtion is not, whether it be <hi>Divine Matter,</hi> or not, but whether a <hi>Divine Conſtitution</hi> or not? and therefore I joyne <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> together: The <hi>Matter</hi> proves not its <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimacy,</hi> unleſs ſuch a <hi>Frame, Method, Compoſure</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of VVorſhip can be proved <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> to be <hi>Chriſts Own. Prayer</hi> is Chriſts own <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> (I commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with them in that) but here is my Crime, I joyne not with them in <hi>Prayer</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Dreſſe</hi> or <hi>Form,</hi> which (though I neither queſtion the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> that <hi>compoſed</hi> it, nor the <hi>Authority</hi> that <hi>impoſed</hi> it, yet) I profeſſedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, is in my weak judgment meerly <hi>Humane;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do not a little wonder that ſuch a man as Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſhould become its <hi>Mecoenas</hi> and <hi>Advocate,</hi> who cannot be ignorant of the unhappy occaſion of the firſt introduction of ſuch <hi>man-deviſed Forms</hi> and <hi>Frames</hi> into the Chriſtian Church, adminiſtred by the prevailing <hi>Arrian</hi> and <hi>Pelagian</hi> hereſies, above three hundred years after Chriſt; nor of the approved Teſtimonies of <hi>Juſtine Martyr, Tertullian,</hi> &amp;c. witneſſing the immunity and freedome of the Church in their dayes from ſuch impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, alleadged by his <hi>SMECTYMN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AN</hi> Brethren: But the grounds of my doubts herein ſhall be diſcloſed in the next anſwer; however you may judge from what hath already been ſaid, how unjuſtly <hi>Non-Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> is interpreted <hi>ſinful Separation,</hi> it being a neceſſary declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of meer <hi>Will-Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> is indeed a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Part of <hi>Real-Solemn</hi> Divine Worſhip, being one of Chriſts <hi>Fundamental Inſtitutions;</hi> but the knowne <hi>Violence</hi> of <hi>Impoſition,</hi> the <hi>Will-Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63806:17"/>which attends the celebration thereof in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (ſo that I cannot communicate with her there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>without ſinne</hi>) does <hi>warrant</hi> and <hi>neceſſitate</hi> my (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) <hi>Non-Communion</hi> and <hi>Withdrawment,</hi> this being clearly Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> alleadged caſe of <hi>Real Inevitable Neceſſity.</hi> Thus then,</p>
            <p>Though the Church of <hi>England</hi> be a <hi>true</hi> Church (ſo that a <hi>Total Separation</hi> from her is unwarrantable) and therefore <hi>Communion</hi> with her in all the parts of <hi>Real-Solemn Divine</hi> Worſhip, wherein I may joyn with her without either <hi>let</hi> or <hi>ſin,</hi> be a <hi>Duty,</hi> yet, her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> appearing to be no part of <hi>Real-Solemne Divine</hi> Worſhip, but a meer <hi>humane Conſtitution;</hi> and the <hi>Supper</hi> (though a Subſtantial Part of <hi>Real-Solemn-Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> VVorſhip, yet) being by <hi>corrupt Mixtures</hi> and <hi>Appurtenances,</hi> much <hi>adulterated,</hi> ſo that I cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate therein <hi>without ſin;</hi> my (preſent) <hi>Non-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with her, in both the one and the other (which is a <hi>Partial Separation</hi>) is ſo far from being a <hi>breach of Duty,</hi> that it is <hi>a Duty,</hi> therefore no <hi>Schiſm,</hi> (the thing charged) which is a <hi>Cauſleſs Separation,</hi> &amp;c. This may acquit me, and all men in my Capacity, from Mr. <hi>Croftons Nick-name</hi> of <hi>Separatiſt</hi> in the Caſe. But I refer you, <hi>Sir,</hi> to my next anſwer for further ſatisfaction in both.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By way of <hi>Retortion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded</hi> in caſe of <hi>Real-inevitable Neceſſity (ex Conceſſis)</hi> by Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own Doctrine and Aſſertion; but <hi>mine</hi> (that I may put in for a <hi>Superſedeas</hi>) is a caſe of <hi>Real inevitable Neceſſity;</hi> therefore (by Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own <hi>Acquittance</hi>) my <hi>Non-Communion, &amp;c.</hi> is no <hi>ſin,</hi> no <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be two things wherein I cannot communicate with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> viz. 1. Her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer:</hi> 2. The Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63806:18"/>her preſent method of <hi>adminiſtration;</hi> for <hi>Non-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> in both which, I alledge a <hi>Real-Inevitable Neceſſity,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of my <hi>Non-Communion</hi> in the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> is grounded on <hi>Invincible doubts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the very <hi>Lawfulneſſe</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and thoſe upon three <hi>Maxims</hi> (ſhall I call them?) or <hi>Principles,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> (poſſibly) would term <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> as well as my <hi>Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Viz: 1. <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions</hi> that are not <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful,</hi> are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions,</hi> that are not <hi>Needful,</hi> are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. That <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> which is not <hi>commanded,</hi> is <hi>forbidden.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>(Which though they may ſeem to be very <hi>Paradoxes,</hi> and ſtrange Poſitions in this age, yet I profeſſe to you (without any cenſorious reflection upon either the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples or Practiſes of others) they hamper me:)</p>
            <p>The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> peculiar to each of thoſe <hi>Propoſitions</hi> containeth my <hi>doubt</hi> —</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution,</hi> which is neither 1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful,</hi> nor (much leſs) 2. <hi>Needful,</hi> nor 3. <hi>Commanded, Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions</hi> which are not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> are not <hi>Lawful,</hi> which are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable,</hi> are <hi>Vnwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable</hi> (where, by that which is <hi>unprofitable</hi> I underſtand that which is <hi>un-edifying</hi>) is a Truth bottomed upon a great <hi>Canon Apoſtolick</hi> (in reſpect of which all <hi>Church-Conſtitutions</hi> ought to be Acts of (True) <hi>Canonical Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> viz:) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let all things be done unto edifying,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.26. Now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Edification</hi> (according to the language of the Holy Ghoſt) is not only, 1. a Freedom from <hi>poſitive dammage;</hi> nor 2. a <hi>Single;</hi> but 3. a <hi>Succeſſive</hi> and <hi>gradual</hi> Benefit: For Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation hereof, I might produce the Joynt-determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63806:18"/>and <hi>Vote</hi> of a whole <hi>Jury</hi> of the Orthodox-Learned. <hi>Calvin, Junius, Tilenus, Alſtedius, Hoſpinian, Beza, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus, Prof. Leidenſ. Jus Canonicum, Perkins,</hi> &amp;c. who unanimouſly conclude the ſame, whoſe ſeveral Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies I ſhould here inſert, but that I muſt ſhun prolixity. 'Tis obſervable what is left upon everlaſting Record, namely, That the <hi>Ceremonial Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> was <hi>diſanulled</hi> becauſe of its <hi>weakneſſe</hi> and <hi>unprofitableneſſe,</hi> Heb. 7.18. (that which may be urged (in my mind) invincibly againſt the retention of <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church) whence I argue,</p>
            <p>If a <hi>Divine Law</hi> (one of <hi>Gods own</hi> making) muſt be reverſed, diſanulled, and aboliſhed, (the Holy Ghoſt himſelf being Judge) becauſe <hi>unprofitable,</hi> (as the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial</hi> was, <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Subſtance</hi> being exhibited) then ſurely <hi>(A fortiori)</hi> all <hi>Humane Laws</hi> (thoſe of <hi>Mens</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, eſpecially <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi>) which are <hi>unprofitable,</hi> are <hi>(hoc ipſo) unwarrantable:</hi> I ſhould not fear to aſſert this in the face of the world. Now</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is a <hi>Conſtitution unprofitable</hi> (which is the <hi>Aſſumption</hi>) will need no great labour to prove. 'Tis <hi>hurtfull,</hi> and is that <hi>uſefull?</hi> who cannot witneſs the unhappy Conſequences, Miſchiefs and Inconveniencies attending it? I ſhould ſay but little, if as ſome call <hi>Ignorance</hi> the <hi>Mother of Devotion,</hi> ſo I ſhould call it, <hi>The Nurſery of Ignorance:</hi> Nay what greater <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> this day in <hi>England?</hi> what hath more divided between Faithful <hi>Paſtors</hi> &amp; their dear <hi>People?</hi> the <hi>Service</hi> hath ſtopt the <hi>Prophets mouths, pad-lock't</hi> thoſe <hi>lips</hi> which <hi>ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve knowledg;</hi> alas! thoſe are but few amongſt the many thouſand <hi>Malignant</hi> Influences of this <hi>Convocation-Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire:</hi> And yet, <hi>There is no hurt in it,</hi> ſay ſome; that's ſtrangel but admit there were not, doth it any <hi>good?</hi> the <hi>Negative</hi> will prove it an <hi>Illegitimate</hi> brood; <hi>yes,</hi> may ſome <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> ſay; and ſo may I ſay of the <hi>Popiſh Miſſal,</hi> it may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally profit me; but neither will <hi>Collateral</hi> nor <hi>ſingle</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63806:19"/>Benefit prove the <hi>Legitimacy</hi> either of the one or of the other: Further; Is it an <hi>Edifying</hi> Conſtitution? if not, caſhier it for <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> 'tis an <hi>Adulterate</hi> piece: <hi>The waters of the Sanctuary</hi> muſt riſe <hi>higher</hi> and <hi>higher;</hi> now what influence hath it in <hi>building</hi> of a man, a Church-member, up <hi>in his moſt holy Faith?</hi> were this to <hi>Edifie?</hi> In a word; It muſt<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit.</hi> lib. 4. c. 10. Sect. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Manifeſtam utilitatem prae ſe ferre,</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Calvins</hi> Rule,) It muſt conduce to the <hi>neanifeſt advantage</hi> of the Church of God, to her <hi>growth</hi> and <hi>gradual Proſiciency</hi> (ſince the riper ſhe is for <hi>age,</hi> the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſhe ſhould be for <hi>knowledge,</hi> &amp;c.) to the <hi>perfecting</hi> of this <hi>Myſtical Building,</hi> Epheſ. 4.11, 12. elſe (beleeve it) it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and if <hi>un-edifying,</hi> then <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable.</hi> Now how little our <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is contributary hereunto, let the Impartial judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions</hi> which are <hi>Vnneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> are (alſo) <hi>Vnlawfull,</hi> (the ſecond Propoſition) ſeems to be firmly grounded on the <hi>Authentick Decretal</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve</hi> of the famous <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> conſiſting of <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> (Men <hi>extraordinarily</hi> gifted, and <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly</hi> guided by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi>) Act. 15.28. <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us, to lay upon you no greater bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den than thoſe neceſſary things:</hi> An <hi>Imitable</hi> and <hi>Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Example</hi> to all <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Convocations</hi> in ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ages; for there the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> Himſelf was <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> (as I may ſay) <hi>it ſeemed good</hi> firſt <hi>to the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and then <hi>to Vs.</hi> 'Twas His Own <hi>Viſum eſt,</hi> and <hi>Canon.</hi> — <hi>All Peace be on them that walk according to this Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is an <hi>Vnneceſſary</hi> Conſtitution (which is the <hi>Aſſumption</hi>), none <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, none of the <hi>Neceſſary things</hi> licenced by the Holy Ghoſt, appears to me from a threefold conſideration, namely, Of 1. <hi>Chriſt;</hi> 2. The <hi>Spirit;</hi> and 3. The <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. All <hi>Neceſſary</hi> Parts of <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> are by <hi>Chriſt</hi> (who is the Churches <hi>Law-maker,</hi> as well as <hi>Peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> the great <hi>Maſter of Aſſemblies</hi>) undoubtedly) <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63806:19"/>and <hi>appointed;</hi> elſe that might be juſtly imputed to the <hi>Son,</hi> from which the Holy Ghoſt acquits the <hi>Servant,</hi> Heb. 3.5. (which were blaſphemy once to imagine,) and 'twere not a little ſtrange, if when the <hi>Man Moſes</hi> did punctually preſcribe all the <hi>Tabernacle-Appurtenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> even to a <hi>Pin</hi> and <hi>Snuffers,</hi> the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> ſhould not alſo be <hi>faithfull over his houſe</hi> in deſcribing and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing all the <hi>neceſſary</hi> Parts of his <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Service;</hi> as if <hi>Scripture-Oeconomicks</hi> were defective and incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Church-Rules</hi> without the Contribution of <hi>Men-devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, additional-traditional</hi> Forms, &amp;c. But now the <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> (that <hi>Conſtitution</hi>) is none of <hi>Chriſts</hi> either in reſpect of <hi>Compoſition,</hi> or (much leſſe) <hi>Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Ergo, &amp;c. Moſt of the <hi>Matter</hi> though I grant to be <hi>Divine,</hi> yet that will not prove the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> (the thing in queſtion) <hi>Divine:</hi> What need many words? For the Lords ſake let either <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Preſident</hi> in either <hi>Chriſt</hi> or his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> be produced for ſuch a <hi>Frame, Contexture</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of worſhip, and the queſtion is deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> is an <hi>Inſtance</hi> and <hi>Preſident,</hi> ſay ſome! 'Tis <hi>Authentique Common-Prayer</hi> indeed, (and that which I reverence for the <hi>Authors</hi> ſake, but not <hi>ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize</hi>) but that it is a <hi>Form,</hi> needs proof; however, be it a <hi>Form,</hi> be it a <hi>Pattern,</hi> it makes nothing againſt me; for if a <hi>Form,</hi> then <hi>Humane Forms</hi> are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary,</hi> (that is my <hi>Quaeſitum</hi>) unleſs men will tax Chriſts <hi>Own</hi> with ſome <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> or <hi>Inſufficiency, — Fruſtra fit per plura,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Religion</hi> abhors <hi>Superfluities</hi> as well as <hi>Nature.</hi> If Chriſt hath accommodated me with a <hi>Divine Form</hi> of Prayer (one of his <hi>Own</hi>) I may by Authority ſlight all <hi>Humane Forms</hi> in the world: Again, If a <hi>Pattern,</hi> then no <hi>Preſident</hi> nor <hi>Protection</hi> to <hi>Set-Forms,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Where the <hi>Spirit of Prayer</hi> is plentifully <hi>effuſed</hi> and <hi>diffuſed,</hi> there <hi>Set-Forms</hi> of Prayer are <hi>unneceſſary;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whatever Benefit can be imagined to accrew from <hi>Forms,</hi> all that and much more doth accrew from the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63806:20"/>
               <hi>Spirit:</hi> Are <hi>Forms</hi> Helps to the <hi>weak?</hi> cannot they <hi>go</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them? The <hi>Spirit helpeth our infirmities,</hi> Rom. 8.26. He being the Chriſtians <hi>Auxiliary</hi> in, as well as the <hi>Author</hi> of prayer: Are <hi>Forms</hi> Guides to the <hi>Blind?</hi> cannot they <hi>ſee</hi> without them? The <hi>Spirits Office</hi> is to—<hi>guide into all Truth,</hi> John 13.16. Now this ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> is plentifully powred out in <hi>Goſpel-times,</hi> being Chriſts <hi>Exaltation-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native,</hi> Act. 2.1, 2, 3, 4. Eph. 4.8. By vertue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath <hi>commenced a degree</hi> above the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church: <hi>This</hi> being ſubjected to a <hi>Servile</hi> and <hi>Infant-ſtate,</hi> (the <hi>Legall Conſtitution,</hi>) That being promoted to a <hi>Filial Adult-State,</hi> (the <hi>Evangelical Conſtitution</hi> of the Church); <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Goſpel</hi> (Chriſts <hi>Canon-Law</hi>) is (as a Perfect <hi>Syſtem</hi> of <hi>Sound Words</hi> and Doctrine, ſo) a Sufficient <hi>Directory</hi> for <hi>Worſhip, able to make the man of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> (2 Tim. 3.15, 16.) without <hi>Humane Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions; Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that <hi>Errour</hi> hath its <hi>Advocates;</hi> 'tis pleaded, That <hi>Set-Forms</hi> of Prayer are <hi>needfull</hi> for maintaining of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> &amp;c. Good Lord! have thoſe <hi>Patrons</hi> no better <hi>Pleas</hi> than what <hi>Adulterate-Rome</hi> may eſpouſe for defence and inſinuation of her <hi>Maſſe-Service,</hi> and <hi>Metropolitical Antichriſtian Head?</hi> Are there no <hi>Church-Ligaments?</hi> no <hi>Bonds</hi> or <hi>Badges</hi> of <hi>Church-Vnity,</hi> but what would inevitably deſtroy <hi>Church-Purity,</hi> if not (eftſoon) <hi>Church-Entity?</hi> Why, will men create more <hi>Neceſſities</hi> than the Word will <hi>warrant,</hi> and thus occaſion more <hi>Sins</hi> than ever God <hi>forbad?</hi> But enough of that. <hi>Sir,</hi> With Your leave I will now conclude that our <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer</hi> is <hi>unneceſſary,</hi> therefore <hi>unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;</hi> not <hi>uſefull,</hi> not <hi>needfull,</hi> therefore not <hi>lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>that</hi> which is not <hi>commanded</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God (<hi>viz.</hi> in poynt of <hi>Matter</hi> or <hi>Manner</hi>) is (conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially) <hi>forbidden,</hi> (the third Propoſition) may be (in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63806:20"/>my Judgment) undeniably concluded from theſe three gradual <hi>Axiomes,</hi> (which are indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Innate, Rational</hi> Principles,) viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>There is a GOD;</hi> This is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Fundamental</hi> Article of our <hi>Faith;</hi> a Truth, which the <hi>Creatures</hi> may ſerve for <hi>Catholick Teachers,</hi> (the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> for an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi>) to <hi>ſchool</hi> us in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Creation-works</hi> are a <hi>Revelation-Book,</hi> which reveals a <hi>God,</hi> though not a <hi>Chriſt;</hi> a <hi>Deity,</hi> though not a <hi>Trinity: Natural Conſcience</hi> is a <hi>Boſom-Volume,</hi> wherein we may read the ſame; which, ſhould a man become a tractable <hi>Diſciple</hi> to, he ſhould never die (in this ſenſe) <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or <hi>Infidel. Davids Fool</hi> may <hi>ſay in his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is no God,</hi> but 'tis not ſaid he (really) <hi>thought</hi> ſo; for this is a Truth, which may be read by <hi>Natures Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Light,</hi> yea, by <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There is Worſhip due from the Creature to this God.</hi> This is a main <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.19.</note> one of the prime things which may by <hi>Natures Light</hi> and <hi>Creature-evidence</hi> be <hi>known of God;</hi> a Principle depending upon the former. That very <hi>Light</hi> which convinceth men of a <hi>God-head,</hi> convinceth them alſo of this <hi>Worſhip</hi> as a <hi>Natural Debt</hi> and <hi>Tribute</hi> due thereunto: Both are <hi>Common-Creed:</hi> Thus the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are not charged with <hi>Ignorance</hi> of a <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> nor with neglect of <hi>Natural Worſhip</hi> (the <hi>Thing</hi>), but with a defect in the <hi>Manner</hi> of <hi>Worſhip, — When they knew God, they glorified him not</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>AS God,</hi> Rom. 1.21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This God is to be worſhipped in a way ſuitable to his own Will and Nature:</hi> What more <hi>Rational</hi> then this? What <hi>Heathen Socrates</hi> aſcribed to his <hi>Idol-God,</hi> ſurely we may, and muſt (much more) aſcribe to Our <hi>Only True God,</hi> namely, that he muſt be worſhipped <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in a way, manner, and method moſt pleaſing to himſelf; and what Manner or Method of Worſhip more pleaſing to God, then <hi>that</hi> which is agreeable to his Own
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63806:21"/>
               <hi>Will,</hi> or moſt <hi>ſuitable</hi> to his own <hi>Nature?</hi> Now then to apply.</p>
            <p>Since there can be no <hi>true Divine Worſhip,</hi> which is not either <hi>ſuitable</hi> to Gods <hi>Nature</hi> (as is <hi>Goſpel-Worſhip,</hi> it being <hi>ſpiritual</hi> as <hi>God</hi> himſelf is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> Joh. 4.24.) or (at leaſt) <hi>agreeable</hi> to Gods <hi>Will</hi> (as the <hi>Jewiſh Worſhip,</hi> by <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Oblations,</hi> the <hi>blood of Buls and Goats,</hi> &amp;c. which had nothing at all to commend it, but the <hi>Quod libet licet,</hi> the very <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> (elſe how <hi>irrational</hi> had it been?) God having by way of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgency,</hi> accommodated the Outward Method and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his <hi>Worſhip</hi> under the <hi>Law</hi> more to the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> then to his <hi>Own;</hi> whereas <hi>Evangelical Worſhip</hi> is not only <hi>agreeable</hi> to his <hi>Will,</hi> but <hi>ſuitable</hi> to his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>). Since the <hi>agreeableneſſe</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> to Gods <hi>Will,</hi> and the <hi>ſuitableneſſe</hi> of Worſhip to his <hi>Nature,</hi> is to be meaſured by the <hi>Manner,</hi> as well as (if not more then) by the <hi>Matter</hi> of it, (<hi>That</hi> being the <hi>Diſtinctive Forme</hi> thereof): And ſince the true <hi>Regular Manner</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip</hi> is only revealed and dictated in and by <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Canon; Scripture Light</hi> directing to the <hi>Manner,</hi> as <hi>Natures Light</hi> directs to the <hi>Object</hi> of Worſhip; (elſe what advantage have <hi>We</hi> to whom are committed <hi>the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God,</hi> over the <hi>Pur-blind Gentiles?</hi> who are not tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>not worſhipping</hi> of <hi>God</hi> according to the light they had, whereby they were directed to the <hi>Object</hi> of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; but for <hi>not glorifying of God AS God,</hi> (Rom. 1.21.) they failed in the <hi>Manner</hi>): Since (I ſay) 'tis ſo, I muſt needs conclude, that <hi>That Manner</hi> or <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which is not <hi>Preſcribed,</hi> is <hi>(ipſo facto) Probihited,</hi> which is not <hi>Commanded,</hi> is (conſequentially at leaſt) <hi>forbidden.</hi> Some (poſſibly) will <hi>Object,</hi> What Reaſon, that That which is not <hi>Commanded,</hi> ſhould (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently) be <hi>forbidden;</hi> more then why that which is not <hi>forbidden,</hi> ſhould be (conſequently) <hi>commanded?</hi> (a common Plea in the Caſe): But, <hi>Diſpar eſt Ratio,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63806:21"/>there is a great diſparity, a <hi>Negative</hi> will prove a <hi>Sin,</hi> but every <hi>Poſitive</hi> will not prove a <hi>Duty;</hi> thus whatever is <hi>not agreeable</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> of God is a <hi>Sin,</hi> but all that is <hi>agreeable</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> of God is not a <hi>Duty;</hi> this is plain, a <hi>Moral Duty</hi> is the <hi>Obligatory Influence</hi> of ſome <hi>Poſitive Law:</hi> To proceed then.</p>
            <p>That ſuch a <hi>Conſtitution</hi> as <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is not <hi>commanded</hi> of God (the <hi>Aſſumption</hi>) is proved aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly: Where is there ever a <hi>Deus dixit,</hi> a <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord</hi> for it in all the Book of God? An <hi>Eccleſia dixit,</hi> will not go down with me, who cannot put <hi>Church-Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility</hi> into my <hi>Creed,</hi> nor ſuffer my ſoul to become <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> to an <hi>Implicite-Faith, Infallibility</hi> is one of Gods own <hi>Crown-Royalties;</hi> He onely is <hi>Infallible</hi> in point of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> who is <hi>Immutable</hi> in <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>Exiſtence.</hi> Where is there ever one <hi>Authentick Preſident</hi> for it? Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> (I know) doth attribute the <hi>Eſſential Form</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> to it (page 25.) which he deſcribes to be, <hi>A calling upon God in the name of Chriſt;</hi> But if he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, in the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Will of Chriſt,</hi> then I ſay, 'Tis not a <hi>Right</hi> Deſcription of <hi>Prayer,</hi> (whoſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eſſentiale</hi>) <hi>Eſſential Form</hi> depends upon the <hi>Rule,</hi> Gods own <hi>Preſcript,</hi> it being a <hi>Moral Duty</hi>) no better then what may agree to the <hi>Romiſh Letany:</hi> But if he do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand therein the <hi>Will of Chriſt,</hi> I once more call for an inſtance in ſome <hi>Authentique Precept</hi> or <hi>Preſident</hi> (the onely <hi>Commentaries</hi> upon Gods <hi>Will Regulative</hi>) for ſuch a <hi>Conſtitution;</hi> which I deſpaire ever to ſee. I might have told you, that it is a <hi>Humane Tradition,</hi> and therefore a ſin againſt the 2. <hi>Commandement,</hi> being contrary to Biſhop<note n="*" place="margin">Expoſ. on 2. Com.</note> 
               <hi>Andrews</hi> his <hi>Modus Praeſcriptus;</hi> Gods own <hi>Preſcribed Manner</hi> of worſhip: But I ſhall not need to go ſo far; let it be proved, that it is a <hi>Conſtitution</hi> whereof <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Author,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> the <hi>Rule,</hi> the <hi>Practice Apoſtolick</hi> the <hi>Pattern;</hi> or what can it be other then <hi>Cultus ex humane cerebro confictus?</hi> meer <hi>Will-Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> which (being<note n="†" place="margin">Sir France Bacon, <hi>in his</hi> Eſſayes.</note> 
               <hi>the reproach of Deity</hi>) muſt needs be as well
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63806:22"/>(though not as much) as <hi>Idolatrous Worſhip</hi> diſpleaſing to Him who with his own finger <hi>twice wrote</hi> Himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A Jealous God;</hi> who therefore may juſtly ſay of ſuch <hi>Officious Service;—Who hath required this at your hand?</hi> O that men would ſeriouſly conſider (what I tremble at the very thoughts of, namely) the dreadfull doom and ſentence gone out againſt ſuch, as either <hi>add</hi> to, or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract</hi> from Gods own <hi>Volume,</hi> Deut. 12.32. Rev. 22.18, 19.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Sir,</hi> a <hi>Conſcience fettered</hi> with <hi>doubts</hi> is that which I plead as a ground of <hi>Real inevitable neceſſity</hi> in this caſe of my <hi>Non-Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> So that whereas Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> pleads for <hi>Communion</hi> with her in that (as well as in other Parts of <hi>Solemn Publique</hi> Worſhip) as a thing not onely <hi>Lawfull,</hi> but <hi>Expedient,</hi> yea, <hi>Indiſpenſably neceſſary,</hi> I queſtion all, viz: not onely the <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> but the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency,</hi> yea the very <hi>Lawfulneſſe</hi> of it, it being in mine opinion upon the accounts aforeſaid, none of the <hi>Real</hi> or <hi>True Worſhip</hi> of God, but meer <hi>Wil-Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> of Men, ſo that I cannot communicate therein <hi>without ſin;</hi> For <hi>To him that eſteemeth a thing unclean, to him it is unclean:</hi> And <hi>he that doubteth is damned, if he eat, becauſe he eateth not of faith, for what is not of faith is ſin,</hi> Rom. 14.14.23. And what though my <hi>Conſcience</hi> be <hi>Erroneous</hi> herein, yet doth it lay upon me a <hi>Negative Obligation</hi> in the caſe, <hi>Ligat,</hi> though not <hi>Obligat;</hi> Though an <hi>Erroneous Conſcience</hi> obliegeth me not to <hi>do</hi> what it <hi>commandeth,</hi> yet it obliegeth me to <hi>refrain</hi> from what it <hi>forbiddeth;</hi> this is the determination of Learned <hi>Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts</hi> in the Caſe: <hi>Conſcience</hi> being the <hi>Queen Regent</hi>-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of the ſoul, Gods Own <hi>Repreſentative</hi> therein, muſt not (at leaſt in matters of <hi>Indifferency</hi>) be controled; For<note n="*" place="margin">Ameſ. de <hi>Conſc.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Quicquid dictat, dictat ſub ratione Voluntatis Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</hi> Better it is that I ſhould not at all communicate, than to communicate with a <hi>Reluctancy</hi> of Conſcience;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63806:22"/>for in ſuch a caſe, what is an <hi>Indifferency</hi> to another, may be <hi>Iniquity</hi> in me; Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhould rather <hi>pity</hi> than <hi>cenſure</hi> ſuch a One; what muſt all be <hi>cut off</hi> that are not skilled in his <hi>Shibboleth?</hi> His Invective againſt <hi>Church-Yard-Loyterers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 12.6.</note> (Page 24.) might well have been ſpared in a time, wherein <hi>Vineyard-Labourers</hi> are ſo few.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Real-Inevitable Neceſſity</hi> of my <hi>Wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>drawment</hi> from, or <hi>Non-Communion</hi> in the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> under the preſent Modes and Methods of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is grounded upon the<note n="*" place="margin">Conſtit. and Can. Eccleſ. <hi>An Dom.</hi> 1603. Can. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Impoſed Geſture,</hi> the <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Corruptions</hi> which attend it: (which who can be ſuch a <hi>ſtranger in</hi> our <hi>Iſrael</hi> as to be ignorant of)? Though I could go neer to approve of the geſture of <hi>Kneeling,</hi> being leſt <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> and commended or practiſed only as an <hi>Outward Badge</hi> of more than ordinary <hi>thankfullneſſe,</hi> under the reception of an <hi>Extraordinary Bleſſing,</hi> and not as an Act of <hi>Piety, Neceſſity,</hi> or <hi>Worſhip:</hi> And though I ſhall not (at this time at leaſt) go ſo far as ſome, namely, to aſſert that the <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Bread</hi> purpoſely ſet before <hi>Superſtitious Kneelers (Proteſtants),</hi> and the (ſuppoſed) <hi>Tranſubſtantiated Bread</hi> purpoſely placed before <hi>Idolatrous Kneelers</hi> (the <hi>Papiſts</hi>) is the ſame, <hi>In Eſſe Ad. rabili;</hi> yet two things I ſhall ſay: Firſt, A <hi>Papiſts Idolatrous Kneeling.</hi> before the <hi>Bread</hi> (ſuppoſed to be <hi>Tranſubſtantiated,</hi> is (in ſome reſpect) more <hi>Excuſable,</hi> than a <hi>Proteſtants Superſtitious Kneeling</hi> before the <hi>Bread</hi> (being onely) <hi>Conſecrated;</hi> for his <hi>Creed</hi> doth (though not <hi>Juſtifie,</hi> yet) in part <hi>excuſe</hi> his <hi>geſture;</hi> Did I beleeve that the <hi>Sacramental Bread,</hi> is no ſooner <hi>Conſecrated,</hi> than really <hi>Tranſubſtantiated</hi> into the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt, I ſhould think, I ſhould greatly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n if I did not forthwith exhibit <hi>Worſhip</hi> thereunto, ſince (as the O tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox-Learned generally grant) there is <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> due to Chriſt even as <hi>Man,</hi> viz: by vertue of the <hi>Perſonal Vnion</hi> of his <hi>Humane</hi> with his <hi>Divine Nature.</hi> Secondly, The geſture of <hi>Kneeling</hi> at the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:63806:23"/>&amp;c. in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> having <hi>Neceſſity</hi> placed in it (elſe why is it <hi>impoſed,</hi> and not ſeft <hi>Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?</hi>) yea and <hi>holineſſe</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> too, (as its<note n="*" place="margin">The Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Spalato:</hi> Dr. <hi>Burgeſſe:</hi> Dr. <hi>Mortoun; Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body,</hi> &amp;c.</note> learned <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons</hi> inform us), and ſo becoming a dangerous piece of <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Will-Worſhip,</hi> I am <hi>warranted</hi> to <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw,</hi> and refuſe <hi>Communion</hi> with her therein, by a <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeas</hi> of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own grant, viz: in caſe of <hi>Real-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable Neceſſity;</hi> with this aſſurance, that <hi>God will have mercy and not ſacrifice.</hi> The <hi>Sacrament</hi> is a <hi>Priviledge,</hi> but <hi>Superſtition</hi> is <hi>Sin;</hi> now I may often warrantably wave a <hi>Priviledge,</hi> but never am I warranted to commit the leaſt <hi>Sin;</hi> and therefore for fear of <hi>Poyſon,</hi> I deny my ſelf <hi>Food.</hi> Alas! Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Inſtances in <hi>Stinking Fiſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pudled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c. An <hi>Vncleane Veſſel,</hi> &amp;c. yeeld not the leaſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to me; what if there be <hi>poyſon</hi> in the diſh, though never ſo well <hi>garniſhed?</hi> My <hi>Dear Friend,</hi> The caſe is very hard; but what ſhall I do? If I muſt dye, let it be by <hi>famine,</hi> as ſoon as by <hi>poyſon,</hi> If I muſt be <hi>fourty years</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> (even as long as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were in the <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> without theirs) <hi>The will of the Lord be done:</hi> I had rather be in the <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> without it, than go <hi>back to Egypt</hi> for it, while I know that I am in the way towards <hi>Canaan;</hi> not ſo getting St. <hi>Bernards Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, Non privatio ſed contemptus damnat;</hi> The <hi>want</hi> of a <hi>Sacrament</hi> is my <hi>Affliction,</hi> but the <hi>Contempt</hi> of it onely (under that want) is my <hi>Sin;</hi> only my prayer is that God would forgive them, <hi>Who make the Lords offering to be abhorred.</hi> Thus <hi>Sir,</hi> I hope you are by this time ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the caſe, namely, That <hi>Non-Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> as alſo in the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> under the preſent method of Adminiſtration, in thoſe who yet joyn with her in <hi>Prayer, Praiſe, The Word Preached</hi> (Parts of <hi>True Solemn Divine Worſhip</hi>) as you and I do) is no <hi>breach of duty,</hi> but <hi>a duty;</hi> (the one being no <hi>True Divine Worſhip,</hi> but <hi>Will-Worſhip;</hi> the other being though a Subſtantial <hi>Part</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:63806:23"/>yet <hi>Adulterated</hi> and extreamly <hi>Corrupted</hi> Worſhip) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no <hi>SCHISM,</hi> which was the thing charged. Now give me leave before I conclude this, to produce my <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> and <hi>Protection</hi> in the caſe, from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> own <hi>Canon</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution;</hi> namely, the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> made in the year, 1603. Entituled <hi>Authors of Schiſms in the Church of England cenſured;</hi> the words whereof are theſe, viz: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall hereafter ſeparate themſelves from the Communion of Saints, as it is approved by the Apoſtles Rules in the Church of England, and combine themſelves together in a new-Brotherhood, accounting the Chriſtians who are conformable to the Doctrine, Government, Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England, Prophane and unmeet for them to joyn with in Chriſtian Profeſſion, let them be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated,</hi> Ipſo facto, &amp;c. Now 1. I ſeparate in caſe of <hi>Real-Inevitable Neceſſity</hi> only, therefore not contrary to the <hi>Apoſtles Rules;</hi> 2. Mine is not <hi>Poſitive Separation,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no <hi>Combination</hi> in a <hi>New-Brotherhood;</hi> 3. I am not only a <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of the ſame <hi>Faith,</hi> (which is all the <hi>Canon</hi> ſeems to require) but a <hi>Partaker</hi> in the ſame <hi>Ordinances,</hi> (though not in all) with thoſe <hi>who are Conformable,</hi> &amp;c. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that very <hi>Canon</hi> which cenſureth <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth <hi>Me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Honoured Sir,</hi> Though I perſwade my ſelf that your requeſt is ſatisfied in the caſe touching <hi>Non-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> &amp;c. Yet cannot I ſatisfie my ſelf unleſs I give a brief touch upon Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> other <hi>Conſiderations;</hi> and before I come to them, aſſoile what is objected from the <hi>High Places</hi> amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> (<hi>A Recocta crambe</hi> with him, and an ordinary Allegation with all that are of his perſwaſion in the caſe in hand).</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do men complain</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as they have cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 39.</note> 
               <hi>That ſome Roman Rites were retained, when this Church was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, let them conſider, many pious Kings of Judah, have their reforming-Governments ſtained with a—But the High Places were not taken away, but the People went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to worſhip, yet I find not that any God-fearing Iſraelites
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63806:24"/>who loathed thoſe Reliques of Idolatry, ever barred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves becauſe thereof from Gods Altar and Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The <hi>Retention</hi> of <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, is (God knows) a juſt cauſe of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,</hi> ſince by reaſon of them, the condition of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Church, is become more <hi>intollerable</hi> than was that of the <hi>Jewiſh Infant</hi> Church; the <hi>Jews</hi> being ſubjected to <hi>Divine Impoſitions,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (oh, ſad!) to <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Preſumptions</hi> (the <hi>Arbitrary Lawes</hi> and <hi>Luſts</hi> of <hi>Men</hi>) witneſſe Sr. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Ad <hi>Januar. Epiſt.</hi> 119. c. 19. Item <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118. c. 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the <hi>Retention</hi> of <hi>Jewiſh-Popiſh Ceremonies</hi> in the Church of <hi>England</hi> at firſt, (when <hi>Reformation</hi> was but <hi>Early</hi>) was a juſt cauſe of Complaint, how much more grievous muſt the <hi>Reduction</hi> of them after <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Expulſion</hi> be? the Firſt compared to that of the laſt 20 years, being as the <hi>Twilight</hi> to a clear <hi>Sunſhine:</hi> It St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complained of the <hi>intollerable burthenſomneſs</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in his dayes, (as in the places before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned) what cauſe have <hi>we</hi> to complain, &amp;c. in our dayes? For if the firſt <hi>Introduction</hi> of them into the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, was a <hi>Reduction</hi> of <hi>Judaiſme,</hi> how like does the <hi>Reduction</hi> of them into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, look to the <hi>Introduction</hi> of <hi>Romaniſme?</hi> what? and not complain!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> alleadged caſe of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and their <hi>High Places,</hi> &amp;c. is (alaſs!) infinitely wide of <hi>Ours;</hi> (and therefore I marvel that a man of ſuch Parts as he is, ſhould once plead the thing): For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Though the <hi>High-Places</hi> of old were, even under <hi>Reforming Governments,</hi> both <hi>retained</hi> and <hi>frequented,</hi> (which I deny not) yet what makes this againſt me, who diſpute not about the <hi>Retention,</hi> but about the <hi>Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of a piece of <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Will-Worſhip?</hi> When did any one of thoſe <hi>Pious Kings</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> firſt <hi>reforme,</hi> and then <hi>reſtore</hi> the <hi>High-Places</hi> ſpoken of? Can Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> inſtance when the <hi>high-Places</hi> were <hi>reſtored</hi> by the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63806:24"/>
               <hi>King,</hi> and frequented by the <hi>People,</hi> after <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn expulſion</hi> of them (to uſe his own words) by Both? O, but <hi>Retrogradations</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> are dangerous! Let me rather <hi>ſojourn</hi> in a <hi>Wilderneſſe,</hi> then <hi>return</hi> to <hi>Egypt;</hi> Alaſs! this is our Caſe: Who can be inſenſible of the <hi>Retrograde Motion</hi> of <hi>Englands Sun?</hi> Our <hi>high-Places</hi> are <hi>reſtored</hi> after <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>ſolemn Expulſion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 18.4.</note> a blaſted <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſhtan</hi> reintroduced: Ah! this is the <hi>Spot</hi> in our <hi>Moon: 'Tis happened to us according to the true Proverb,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>The Dog is turned to his Vomit, and the Sow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the Mire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were confined in their <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Oblations</hi> to <hi>Gods Altar,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> at firſt in the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> Lev. 17.3, 4. and afterwards in the <hi>Temple,</hi> Deut. 12.5, 6, 11. from which it was not lawful, but upon <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> occaſions, or by <hi>divine Inſpiration,</hi> to ſeparate;) God having determined upon the <hi>Place,</hi> as well as the <hi>Manner,</hi> of his Worſhip in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church: No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then, if the <hi>God-fearing Iſraelites</hi> did not barr them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from <hi>Gods Altar</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> notwithſtanding thoſe <hi>Reliques of Idolatry,</hi> ſince they ſhould have in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tranſgreſſed a <hi>Poſitive Law.</hi> Now will Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> argue from hence, againſt the Practice of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom the <hi>Place</hi> of VVorſhip is a meer Matter of <hi>Indifferency, Local-Liberty</hi> being a part of <hi>Goſpel Liberty,</hi> (as hath been cleared above)?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the <hi>High-Places</hi> were originally deviſed by the <hi>Idolatrous Iſraelites</hi> in imitation of the <hi>Heatheniſh Groves,</hi> yet the <hi>uſe</hi> of them was changed by the <hi>God-fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Iſraelites,</hi> who (even the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being of the number, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.39.) perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> in an <hi>Idolatrous Place:</hi> Now will Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> infer from the <hi>Iſraelites worſhipping</hi> in an <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Place,</hi> a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Communion</hi> in a <hi>Superſtitious Worſhip?</hi> My <hi>Friend,</hi> I diſtinguiſh between <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Communion.</hi> The Devout <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were <hi>preſent</hi> in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63806:25"/>an <hi>Idolatrous Place,</hi> but did not therein <hi>partake</hi> of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Worſhip:</hi> Now, What does Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> plead for? Is it my <hi>Preſence</hi> only in the Church at the time of <hi>Divine Service</hi> (as it is called)? or is it <hi>Communion</hi> in that <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice?</hi> To be plain with you; The former I could give, and yet refuſe the latter, but ſo, as That alſo ſhall be the fruit of cogent <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> (not of <hi>Choice</hi>) hoping in that caſe for <hi>Naamans Diſpenſation,</hi> 2 Kings 5.18, 19. (it that ſenſe be received) <hi>Preſence</hi> is a <hi>Civil,</hi> but <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> a <hi>Religious</hi> Act, ſo that ſhould I in Obedience to a <hi>Poenal</hi> Law, or out of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of hearing of a ſoul-ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon, give my <hi>Perſonal Preſence</hi> in the publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in time of <hi>Common-Prayer, knowing that an Idol is nothing in the World,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.4. let none conclude from my <hi>Preſence</hi> in the <hi>Place, Communion</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip,</hi> (or rather <hi>Will-Worſhip</hi>): <hi>Naaman</hi>'s <hi>Servile preſence</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon</hi> (being granted) would not prove his <hi>Communion</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> 2 Kings 5. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> could look upon <hi>Baals Prophets</hi> Sacrificing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. <hi>God-fearing Iſraelites</hi> did fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the <hi>High-Places,</hi> but that proves them not <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants</hi> in the <hi>Superſtition</hi> or <hi>Idolatry</hi> of thoſe Places: Their <hi>Practice</hi> then herein, are but weak Premiſes to Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Concluſion. Once more;</p>
            <p n="4">4. The diſparity between the caſe of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and that of ours, lies greatly in this, <hi>viz.</hi> There the <hi>Worſhip</hi> was <hi>good,</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> only <hi>bad;</hi> but here the <hi>Place</hi> only is <hi>good,</hi> and the <hi>Worſhip</hi> (being meer <hi>Will-Worſhip</hi>) <hi>bad:</hi> So that Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Inference drawn from the <hi>Jewiſh Practice,</hi> in that caſe, againſt <hi>Non-Communion,</hi> &amp;c. is (with me) a manifeſt <hi>non ſequitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONSID. 2. <hi>Communion with the Church under many and great Corruptions, is not inconſiſtent with Zeal, Care, and Conteſt for Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63806:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Remonſ.</hi> 1. That the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the Church is a <hi>Duty</hi> incumbent upon every Man and Member thereof, to be purſued within the <hi>Verge</hi> of their reſpective <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Capacities,</hi> by all <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Lawful Means,</hi> is a Truth here ſuppoſed, and hereafter (<hi>Page</hi> 28.34.) aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> himſelf: Certain it is, that every <hi>Church-Member</hi> ought to be in this reſpect a <hi>Church-Reformer:</hi> And according as his <hi>Capacity</hi> ſhall vary, whether in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>Power, Intereſt, Office</hi> or <hi>Opportunity,</hi> &amp;c. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly doth his <hi>Obligation</hi> hereunto, vary alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> had done well to have ſtated the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion aright <hi>de Eccleſia Reformanda, &amp; de Eccleſia Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata:</hi> The Queſtion with us, is not, Whether <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Church under many and great Corruptions be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Zeal, Care,</hi> and <hi>Conteſt</hi> for <hi>Reformation</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Who will deny that? But this, Whether <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> under <hi>many</hi> and <hi>great Corruptions</hi> be conſiſtent with <hi>due</hi> and <hi>conſtant endeavours</hi> of <hi>reforming,</hi> after <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>ſolemn Expulſion</hi> of the ſame? Nay <hi>Sir,</hi> more particularly yet, 'Tis this (and I would Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> had well conſidered it, <hi>viz.</hi>) Whether <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> (not <hi>under,</hi> but) <hi>in</hi> thoſe very <hi>Corruptions</hi> which (he ſays) we are by a <hi>Duty-Obligation bound</hi> (in our <hi>Capacities</hi>) to <hi>reform,</hi> be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with <hi>due</hi> and <hi>conſtant endeavours</hi> of <hi>reforming</hi> the ſame? More particularly yet, Whether <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> (That (once) <hi>Exploded Will-Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Corrupt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi>) be conſiſtent with that <hi>Tie,</hi> whereby we are <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>conſtant endeavours</hi> of <hi>Reformation?</hi> The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion thus ſtated, who cannot but reſolve into the <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive?</hi> Eſpecially, if he conſider, that the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is not a <hi>Luxurious Branch,</hi> which ought to be <hi>lopt off,</hi> but an <hi>Adulterate Plant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 15.13.</note> which ought to be <hi>rooted out,</hi> as being none of <hi>thoſe Plants which our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father hath planted;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Reformation</hi> herein oblieged to, muſt conſiſt not in an <hi>Alteration,</hi> but in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63806:26"/>outer <hi>Ejection</hi> and <hi>Abrogation</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> (but ſuch as is to be endeavoured only in our ſeveral <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Capacities,</hi> and by <hi>Lawful</hi> and <hi>Warrantable Means: Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Sedition, Faction,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> I am taught of God to abhor, as well and as much as doth Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> himſelf.) Now then, If I be bound to contribute by all lawful endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, what in me lies, &amp; in my capacity, to the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (that is, to the <hi>Extirpation</hi>) of ſuch an <hi>Adulterate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> (viz. the <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi>), how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with ſuch a <hi>Tie</hi> muſt my <hi>Communication</hi> in that worſhip be! VVere not this to <hi>plant</hi> what I am bound to <hi>root up?</hi> and to <hi>build</hi> what I am bound to <hi>deſtroy?</hi> Or if I ſhould after <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>ſolemn Ejection</hi> thereof, <hi>re-embrace</hi> or <hi>countenance</hi> or <hi>communicate</hi> in it, were not that to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> with the <hi>Dog</hi> to the old <hi>Vomit?</hi> to <hi>re-build</hi> our (once) demoliſhed <hi>High-Places?</hi> and is this to <hi>reform? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance</hi> is to Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> (Page 28.) an Argument of <hi>Affection;</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> is to me an Argument of <hi>Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance:</hi> Ah!<note place="margin">Rom. 14.22,</note> my <hi>Good Friend, Happy is he that condemneth not himſelf, in that thing which he alloweth.</hi> How can I <hi>countenance</hi> or <hi>communicate</hi> in that <hi>Worſhip,</hi> whereof I am <hi>bound conſtantly to endeavour</hi> the <hi>Reformation?</hi> Yes, ſaith Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> very well, while the <hi>Matter</hi> is good, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Mode</hi> or <hi>Method</hi> only bad: This is his <hi>Recocta Cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be,</hi> but he muſt prove the <hi>Whole Frame</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> good, which as yet he hath not done, elſe 'tis but a meer evaſion. Now let me ask, What is it that he is bound to <hi>reform?</hi> Is it the <hi>Matter</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> &amp;c.? Or the <hi>Outward Mode</hi> only? or the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> and <hi>Whole Frame</hi> of ſuch a VVorſhip? the <hi>Whole Frame</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> ſurely, a piece of <hi>Adulterate Worſhip,</hi> elſe why was it ever wholly <hi>exploded</hi> and <hi>ejected?</hi> But This <hi>Reformation</hi> is to be <hi>endeavoured</hi> only in our ſeveral <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Capacities:</hi> Truth, Buth the <hi>Negative</hi> Part obliegeth <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> thus, Though I cannot <hi>go on,</hi> yet I am bound <hi>never to go back;</hi> my <hi>Progreſs</hi> may be obſtructed, but my <hi>Regreſs</hi> is not the reby warranted; If my <hi>Sun</hi> be hindered in its <hi>Courſe,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:63806:26"/>let it <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> rather then <hi>goe, one,</hi> much leſs, <hi>ten degrees backward:</hi> My <hi>Poſitive endeavours</hi> may be <hi>ad extrinſeco</hi> obviated, ſo that I <hi>can</hi> not <hi>reform,</hi> but the <hi>Moral Obligation</hi> cannot be violated, ſo that I <hi>muſt</hi> not <hi>retreat;</hi> the <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> is the leaſt that I am in the caſe oblieged to: Now, If by Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own Rule, (Page 28.) <hi>Error cui non reſiſtitur, approbatur,</hi> the <hi>non-reſiſtance</hi> of <hi>Errour</hi> (viz. when 'tis in our power to give a ſtop) be an <hi>Allowance</hi> of it, and <hi>Connivance</hi> be an <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Argument</hi> of <hi>Affection,</hi> what muſt <hi>Perſonal Communion</hi> in the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> be? ſurely an Act and Argument of, <hi>Connivance</hi> in, <hi>Allowance</hi> of, and <hi>Affection</hi> to it: And how inconſiſtent this is with his alleadged <hi>Zeal, Care,</hi> and <hi>Conteſt</hi> for (and <hi>due uninterrupted Endeavours</hi> of) <hi>Reformation,</hi> &amp;c. let the impartial judg. <hi>Sir,</hi> I need not to tell you that I am under no Obligation from the <hi>Oath,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Solemn League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> (I never took <hi>That,</hi> more then the ſlaviſh <hi>Engagement,</hi> which you well know); who then can imagine that I ſhould once plead That? But had it been my ſad Lot to be, either through a <hi>Precipitant Zeal</hi> (the <hi>Predominant humour</hi> of former Times) <hi>entangled,</hi> or by the <hi>circumventing Perſwaſives</hi> of <hi>Covenant-Zealots, inveagled,</hi> into ſuch a <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> and yet <hi>free,</hi> yea, <hi>forward</hi> with Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> and other Reverend and VVorthy <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters,</hi> to ſwallow down <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and to <hi>proſelyte</hi> others to <hi>Communion</hi> therein, I ſhould have owned my ſelf a perpetual Debtour to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> for a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe,</hi> whoſe <hi>Wiſdome</hi> judged it fit to open a door of <hi>Liberty</hi> by diſanulling that <hi>Oath.</hi> But I go on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> (ſaith he (whereof <hi>Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Non-Communion</hi> is the <hi>Privative Part</hi>) <hi>though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 30.</note> 
               <hi>yet are in themſelves vaſtly different, inconſiſtent, and deſtructive each to other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. 1. <hi>Separation</hi> from the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> is an Act of <hi>Reformation,</hi> being a <hi>Continuation</hi> of <hi>Reforming Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> in this juncture of time, wherein <hi>Scrupulous Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> are loth to contribute to the <hi>maintaining</hi> of That by
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63806:27"/>their <hi>Practice,</hi> which after <hi>Solemn Ejection,</hi> is <hi>returned</hi> and <hi>retained</hi> by <hi>Power.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Negative Reformation;</hi> an Act of <hi>Primitive</hi> Zeal; whereby thoſe Perſons refuſe to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> to, what they cannot (poſitively) <hi>reforme;</hi> the ſame Principle oblieging them to <hi>decline</hi> and <hi>diſown</hi> it, when (after <hi>Expulſion</hi>) <hi>reſtored,</hi> that at firſt oblieged them (and poſſibly Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> too) to that <hi>Expulſion;</hi> 'Twere ſtrange if it ſhould be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Separation ſinfull,</hi> and <hi>Reformation,</hi> are indeed <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent,</hi> and <hi>deſtructive each to other: Virtus ſtat in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio: Reformation</hi> (which ſuppoſeth <hi>(hurch Entity)</hi> is an Act of Vertue, equally oppoſite to thoſe Extreams, <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> (the <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> the two <hi>Rocks,</hi> upon either of which, the <hi>Myſticall Ark</hi> (the Church) is in danger of being <hi>ſplit</hi>) the one being deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive to <hi>Church-Purity,</hi> the other to <hi>Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> (as hath been ſaid), ſo that, That very Principle, which obliegeth to <hi>Reformation</hi> (be it <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>Conſcience</hi> under ſuch or ſuch <hi>Enforcements,</hi> &amp;c.) doth <hi>ipſo facto</hi> obliege to an <hi>Equal abhorrency</hi> and <hi>deteſtation</hi> of <hi>Both:</hi> And thus, <hi>Schiſm,</hi> I abominate, 'tis a thing my Soule loathes, I deſire to <hi>keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit, in the Bond of Peace</hi> (Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> wrongs me if he thinks otherwiſe), for I am ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently apprehenſive, how neer, <hi>Church-Rents</hi> border up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Church-Ruine.</hi> But now, That <hi>Separation</hi> onely is <hi>Sinful</hi> and <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> which is <hi>Cauſeleſſe,</hi> and not <hi>war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted</hi> by the (often mentioned) Caſe of <hi>Real-Inevitable-Neceſſity;</hi> which will acquit me from ſuch an Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who communicate with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Prayer, Praiſe,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> Parts of <hi>True Divine Worſhip,</hi> but decline, and modeſtly refuſe Communion with her onely in thoſe two things; viz: 1. Her <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer;</hi> 2. The Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> under the preſent <hi>Method of Adminiſtration</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendices;</hi> the firſt appearing to be no part of Chriſts <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Worſhip;</hi> the ſecond (though for <hi>ſubſtance</hi> a Part of Chriſts <hi>Inſtituted Worſhip,</hi> yet) being by <hi>Superſtition</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63806:27"/>and <hi>Adulterate Mixtures</hi> of <hi>Phariſaical Leaven</hi> with the <hi>Sacramental Bread,</hi> &amp;c. ſo extreamly <hi>corrupted,</hi> that I cannot communicate with her therein <hi>without ſin;</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not partake of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but that I muſt partake of the attending <hi>Superſtition</hi> too; I cannot celebrate the <hi>Death-memorial</hi> of a <hi>Crucified Lord,</hi> but that I muſt by ſin <hi>crucifie</hi> that <hi>Lord afreſh,</hi> and thus <hi>Commemorate</hi> his <hi>Death</hi> with his <hi>Death.</hi> I muſt add,</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a <hi>Separation Paſſive,</hi> whereby <hi>Paſtors</hi> are ſeparated from their <hi>People</hi> (their <hi>Charge</hi>) and a <hi>breach</hi> made upon their <hi>Joynt-Communion;</hi> Hereby judge who are the greateſt <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> Thoſe who are <hi>ſeparated,</hi> being by a <hi>Violent Interruption</hi> at firſt <hi>driven away,</hi> and by <hi>Prevalent Corruptions</hi> (at leaſt in the Things juſt now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) <hi>kept away,</hi> and barred from <hi>Communion,</hi> &amp;c. or, Thoſe who <hi>cauſe</hi> that <hi>Separation:</hi> This is a <hi>Poenal</hi> Evil, the Condigne puniſhment of our <hi>Laodicean Neutrality</hi> and <hi>Lukewarmneſſe</hi> in the work of <hi>Reformation;</hi> there have been in former times too too many <hi>Jehu-like Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> who have made <hi>Religion</hi> to ſtoop to a <hi>Carnal Intereſt,</hi> to <hi>Secular</hi> and <hi>Selfiſh Ends</hi> and <hi>Aimes;</hi> this hath <hi>kindled a fire in Heaven,</hi> which nothing but <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears,</hi> &amp;c. can <hi>quench;</hi> for This,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.21.</note> 
               <hi>A fire is kindled againſt Jacob, and anger alſo is come up againſt our Brittiſh-Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 43.28.</note> Ah! for this hath God <hi>profaned the Princes of the Sanctuary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot</hi> (ſaith he, page 31.) <hi>without trembling conſider the Circumciſed Sects in the Church of Corinth are charged to have left the Head, by leaving the Body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.19.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This is a ſtrange Argument to be urged againſt his cenſured <hi>Non-Communicants,</hi> unleſs they be proved to be (ſuch as by his own confeſſion, thoſe whom the Apoſtle there taxeth, were, viz:) <hi>Circumciſed Sects,</hi> or guilty of ſuch <hi>Corruptions</hi> as will amount to a — <hi>Not hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Head,</hi> the thing there charged upon thoſe <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Sects,</hi> and as juſtly chargeable upon all <hi>Judaizing Chriſtians,</hi> who contend for the <hi>Introduction</hi> and <hi>Retenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63806:28"/>of the <hi>Antiquated, Jewiſh Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Joh. 4.3.</hi> Qui negat Chriſtum in Carne veniſſe, Ive eſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtus. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. lib.</hi> de car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Chriſti.</note> for this is (virtually) to deny that the Son of God is come in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> He being the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Subſtance preſigured</hi> and <hi>ſhaddowed</hi> thereby; This is <hi>Real Antichriſtianiſm;</hi> Enough to turn a <hi>Bethel</hi> into a <hi>Bethaven!</hi> Now who in <hi>England</hi> are moſt <hi>Criminal</hi> herein, who moſt expoſed to the <hi>Apoſtolick Cenſure,</hi> let an <hi>Altar</hi> and <hi>Organ,</hi> and other <hi>Romiſh Reliques</hi> and <hi>Jewiſh Popiſh Ceremonies,</hi> witneſſe: Ah<note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 6 32.</note> 
               <hi>Jerub-baals</hi> are rare in our age. Is this <hi>Reformation?</hi> Yes, ſuch another as was that of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Eighth, when he had renounced the <hi>Popiſh Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> but retained the <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> whom <hi>Luther,</hi> (that great <hi>German-Reformado</hi>) upbraided with a— <hi>He hath killed the Popes Body, but ſaved his Soul:</hi> Yet</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Church is Gods <hi>Ark of Salvation,</hi> and therefore not to be <hi>totally</hi> and <hi>univerſally</hi> forſaken, upon perill of inevitable Ruine, is a received principle with me. The Church is both an <hi>Ark</hi> of <hi>Safety,</hi> and an <hi>Ark</hi> of <hi>Plenty;</hi> It ſaves both from <hi>drowning</hi> and <hi>ſtarving: Noahs Ark</hi> ſaved from the <hi>Deluge,</hi> all that were in it, and none but thoſe: The <hi>Ark</hi> under the Law contained in it three things, viz: <hi>Aarons Rod,</hi> the <hi>Tables of Teſtimony,</hi> the <hi>Pot of Manna,</hi> Heb. 9.4. This <hi>Ark</hi> repreſented the <hi>Church; Aarons Rod, Diſcipline;</hi> the <hi>Tables of Teſtimony,</hi> the <hi>Word;</hi> and the <hi>Pot of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> the <hi>Sacrament:</hi> Where is either <hi>Soul-Safety,</hi> or <hi>Soul-Plenty,</hi> to be had but within the <hi>Verge</hi> and <hi>Limits</hi> of the <hi>Church?</hi> This is the only <hi>Ark</hi> that can <hi>land</hi> us <hi>ſafe</hi> at the <hi>Heavenly Haven, the Land of Reſt;</hi> ſo that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Separation</hi> muſt needs foreſtall <hi>Salvation:</hi> But enough of that. <hi>Generalia non pungunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONSID. 3.<note place="margin">Page 37.</note> 
               <hi>Scandal is an Argument of no ſtrength, when pleaded to ſuperſede, or condemn a Poſitive duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remonſ.</hi> 1. Who denies that? But <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> (it being none
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63806:28"/>of Chriſts <hi>Inſtituted Worſhip</hi>) is not as yet proved to be a <hi>Poſitive du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: What Communion hath light with darkneſs?</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14.16. But 2. <hi>Scandal</hi> is an Argument of ſtrength, when pleaded in matters of <hi>Indifferency</hi> (by his own confeſſion, P. 39.) now ſuch I hope he will grant (which I cannot as yet do) our <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> to be, unleſs he ſay as a Reverend <hi>Biſhop</hi> (one of the greateſt in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) once upon occaſion ſaid to me; who when I humbly deſired to know wherein the <hi>weak</hi> were to be <hi>indulged,</hi> was pleaſed to reſolve it into Things <hi>Indifferent;</hi> and I aſſuming that a <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is a Thing <hi>Indifferent,</hi> replyed, 'Tis not <hi>Indifferent</hi> when <hi>impoſed:</hi> And then, ſarewell <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> for there is nothing <hi>Indifferent</hi> (in <hi>Actu exercito,</hi> or) when <hi>impoſed.</hi> But <hi>Right Reverend Fathers, &amp;c.</hi> what a wofull caſe is this? You tell us, that in things <hi>Indifferent</hi> we are to <hi>indulge</hi> the <hi>weak;</hi> and yet by reaſon of your <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> you leave nothing <hi>Indifferent;</hi> far be it from <hi>You</hi> to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>Neceſſary</hi> by <hi>Your Law,</hi> which (you grant) ſhould be left <hi>Arbitrary</hi> by <hi>Gods Own:</hi> There is an <hi>Indulgency</hi> (you grant) allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (Rom. 14.13, 15, 21. 1 Cor. 8.9, 13.) and yet how are we abridged of it by the <hi>Laws of Men?</hi> Is this <hi>Charity?</hi> or is it <hi>Sacriledge?</hi> Now 3. VVhy may not <hi>Scandal</hi> accrue from Mr. <hi>Croftons Communion</hi> in, as well as from his <hi>Conformity</hi> to the <hi>Common-Prayer?</hi> May not a <hi>weak</hi> Brother hereby <hi>ſuffer</hi> in the <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience,</hi> being <hi>racked</hi> between his own <hi>doubts</hi> and the <hi>Offenders Practice?</hi> Or, may not this adminiſter to him an occaſion of <hi>ſinning,</hi> either in his <hi>condemning</hi> of that which may be <hi>Lawful</hi> to Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> ſeeming <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> to him; or, in <hi>doing</hi> what yet he <hi>condemns</hi> or <hi>doubteth</hi> of, being animated thereunto by Mr, <hi>Croftons</hi> Practice? Or, may not this tend to the <hi>hardening</hi> of men in ſin? And is not this Real <hi>Scandal,</hi> being <hi>Factum quo alius dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior redditur?</hi> (Amandus Polanus, <hi>Synt. Theol. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3.) I dare ſay ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Non-Conforming Miniſters,</hi> who have judged a <hi>ſet Form</hi> of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be <hi>Lawful</hi> in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> and therefore a thing which might be <hi>uſed</hi> without any <hi>treſpaſs</hi> upon either the Law of <hi>Piety</hi> (the <hi>Word</hi>), or the Law of <hi>Purity (Conſcience),</hi> who yet would have totally declined it upon the account of the Law of <hi>Charity,</hi> fearing leaſt they ſhould <hi>deſtroy him</hi> (or them) <hi>with</hi> their <hi>meat, for whom Chriſt died,</hi> Rom. 14.15. Now 'twere ſtrange if this were an Argument ſtrong enough
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63806:29"/>againſt <hi>Conformity,</hi> and yet an Argument of no ſtrength againſt <hi>Communion.</hi> But <hi>Scandal</hi> in this caſe is <hi>Offence taken</hi> only, not <hi>given?</hi> This is as Common as the Prayer it ſelf, but 'tis aſſumed <hi>gratis.</hi> However 4. Admit it were <hi>ſcandalum accep um,</hi> an <hi>offence taken,</hi> and <hi>groundleſs:</hi> Shall there be no <hi>Indulgency</hi> ſhewed in that caſe? What ſhall we think of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the Primitive times? the <hi>weaker</hi> had no <hi>cauſe</hi> or <hi>ground</hi> to be <hi>offended</hi> with the <hi>ſtronger</hi> about their <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> uſe of <hi>mean,</hi> Chriſt having purchaſed for them an <hi>abſclute liberty</hi> therein; &amp; yet what ſtrict laws are by St. <hi>Paul</hi> enacted, againſt the <hi>ſcandalizing</hi> of ſuch? and is it nor his own <hi>Perſonal Reſolve</hi> in the caſe, to become a perpetual <hi>Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bell,</hi> rather than a <hi>Debtor</hi> to the law of <hi>Charity?</hi> (1 Cor. 8 13.) This was my Reply to that Reverend <hi>Biſhop,</hi> when he was pleaſed to aſſert, that the <hi>weak</hi> are not at all to be <hi>indulged,</hi> where there is no <hi>cauſe</hi> or <hi>ground</hi> of <hi>offence;</hi> (and if there be any <hi>real ground</hi> of <hi>offence,</hi> how can they be called <hi>weak?</hi>) ſtrange <hi>Dioceſian</hi> Doctrine!</p>
            <p>CONSI. 4. <hi>I am not without the Caution and Conduct of the ſeber Godly, Learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters &amp; Purjuers of a Perfect &amp; Compleat Reformation. Remon</hi> 1. 'Tis ſtrange Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhould argue from <hi>Communion</hi> amongſt <hi>Diſtinct Churches,</hi> againſt the preſent <hi>Non-Communion</hi> of <hi>Particular Members</hi> of one &amp; the ſame Church; ſince that which is between the other <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches, and this of <hi>England,</hi> is a <hi>Communion,</hi> not by way of <hi>Participation</hi> or <hi>Joynt-Fellowſhip</hi> &amp;c. but of <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the fame true <hi>Religion</hi> only, which I have here owned, and aſſerted. 2. There are indeed <hi>Liturgies uſed</hi> (though not <hi>impoſed</hi>) in ſome of thoſe <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches, But (though they are not <hi>Mala peruſe</hi> yet) this proves them not <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique</hi> more than the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites Sacrificing</hi> in the <hi>High Places</hi> (1 Chr. 16.39.) proves thoſe <hi>Lawful;</hi> why then may they not be looked upon as <hi>Spots</hi> in <hi>their Feaſts?</hi> God conniving at thoſe in <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as He did at <hi>Polygamy</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> which yet he did not approve of. 3. Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Inſtance in the <hi>Primitive Non-Conformiſts</hi> is wide of that of the <hi>Modern;</hi> for our <hi>Communion in</hi> the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> were a <hi>Relapſe</hi> and <hi>Return</hi> into (I am loath to ſay) an <hi>Egyptian darkneſs,</hi> after a <hi>Noon-day Sunſhine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and that (by Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own grant) after <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Solemn Ex ulſion</hi> thereof; now <hi>Prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> are no <hi>Patterns</hi> of a <hi>Retrogradation;</hi> ah! this may humble <hi>Englands declining Sun! lengthned Shaddowe:</hi> (Jer. 4.6.)! 'Tis <hi>Low Water</hi> in the <hi>Sanctuary!</hi> out <hi>Engliſh Ark</hi> is retarded in Her <hi>Voyage</hi> Heaven-ward! <hi>Wind bound</hi> by <hi>Ser-Forms,</hi> &amp;c. ſaint <hi>Gailes</hi> of the <hi>Spirit!</hi> perſwaded I am, were thoſe <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> now alive, they would be loth to become <hi>Baals</hi> (either) <hi>Advocates</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents.</hi> 4. What does Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> think of the <hi>thouſands</hi> of <hi>Non Conforming</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in our days, who (in my mind) deſerve the name of, <hi>Church,</hi> as well as any <hi>Papal Conclave,</hi> or, <hi>Prelatical Convocation</hi> in the world: But however 5. I muſt not draw every <hi>Example</hi> into a <hi>Rule, Judaizing Peters</hi> I muſt not pattern by; Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> and his <hi>Liturgy-Communicant-Fellow Preſbyters.</hi> I reſpect and reverence; but he he a MOSES, be he an AARON I have no warrant to <hi>follow</hi> him any further then he is a <hi>Follower of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.1.</p>
            <p>Now Dear <hi>Sir,</hi> The good <hi>Spirit</hi> of God be your <hi>Convoy</hi> to guid you through the <hi>Syrtes</hi> of this World in a ſtraight courſe <hi>Canaan</hi>-ward, that you may not ſplit upon the Rock, either of <hi>Church-rending Separation</hi> on the one, nor <hi>Church-Adulterating-Superſtition</hi> on the other hand, till he at length <hi>land</hi> you ſale <hi>within the Vail.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63806:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
